<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Management on Sohan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://smsohan.com/categories/management/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Management on Sohan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://smsohan.com/categories/management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Change</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/08/31/change/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/08/31/change/</guid>
      <description>Manager&amp;rsquo;s Mind As managers, we have the benefit of view because we have our eyes on longer term goals. To achieve those goals, we often have to introduce a change. For example, we may want to change how a team is formed or what product a team works on based on new business needs or opportunities. So, we put a lot of thought into it and propose our plan to the team hoping the following reaction:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When I Applied KonMari to My Calendar</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/07/17/when-i-applied-kon-mari-to-my-calendar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/07/17/when-i-applied-kon-mari-to-my-calendar/</guid>
      <description>“I&amp;rsquo;d like to tidy up the entire planet. I would go anywhere if there were something that needs tidying.” - Marie Kondo&#xA;Well, she came to my work calendar in spirit. Let’s start with some backstory.&#xA;When I was developer, my typical day looked like this: one standup meeting and then pretty much the rest of the day in coding. Sometimes I paired up or jumped on a whiteboard session with my coworkers to hash things out.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>People Management and Diagnosing Low Performance</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/05/18/engineering-management-and-diagnosing-low-performance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/05/18/engineering-management-and-diagnosing-low-performance/</guid>
      <description>Beginning with a story here. Back in 2008, I was a couple of years out of college and working for a software company in Dhaka, Bangladesh. Like many of my classmates from my college, I was studying GRE alongside my job for a PhD admission in a reputable US university. That process being long and uncertain, I also applied for an MBA program at the University of Dhaka as a backup plan.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
