<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ruby on Rails on Sohan's Blog</title><link>http://smsohan.com/categories/ruby-on-rails/</link><description>Recent content in Ruby on Rails on Sohan's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://smsohan.com/categories/ruby-on-rails/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Ruby on Rails: Database Migration and Downtime</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/03/18/ruby-on-rails-database-migration-and-downtime/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/03/18/ruby-on-rails-database-migration-and-downtime/</guid><description>Recently, we had a production outage for a few minutes due a database migration on one of our Ruby on Rails apps. The deployment went fine through a few stages, but the problem only showed up at the last and the largest stage. This is exactly what happened during the deploy process.
New code was deployed. Restart was pending, so the server was still running old code. Migrations ran. One migration removed a column that was used in the old code, but no longer used in the new code.</description></item><item><title>Are ActiveRecord Callbacks Any Good?</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/02/07/activerecord-callbacks/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/02/07/activerecord-callbacks/</guid><description>Wanted to share my thoughts on ActiveRecord Callbacks. I&amp;rsquo;d like to know your thoughts if you disagree. Please use the comments.
Only use them when the behavior is must have under all situations, including your tests. For example, we know email addresses are case-insensitive. So no matter what, we may always want to store a lower cased version in the db. #Good class User &amp;lt; ActiveRecord::Base before_save :downcase_email def downcase_email email.</description></item><item><title>Seed Data in a Rails Project</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/11/23/seed-data-in-a-rails-project/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/11/23/seed-data-in-a-rails-project/</guid><description>Most applications I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on required some kind of seed data. For example, I&amp;rsquo;ve used seed data to create a super admin user so the site can actually be used upon a fresh install. Some other common cases include things like, list of credit card types, names of countries/states etc. This post is about some ideas to manage thsese seed data in a Ruby on Rails project.
Where to put the seed data?</description></item></channel></rss>