<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Sohan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://smsohan.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Sohan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://smsohan.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>2022, Oh My!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2022/12/28/2022_oh_my/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2022/12/28/2022_oh_my/</guid>
      <description>I’m personally happy with where things are at the end of this year. We’re on a vacation to visit our family after three years. My kids met some of their cousins for the first time and they’re incredibly excited to get the attention from the extended family. Living in a country half a globe away from our origin means they hardly ever get to experience the warmth of the family and Covid made everything so much harder for the last few years.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2021 → 2022</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/12/19/2021-to-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/12/19/2021-to-2022/</guid>
      <description>My 2021 resolution was to be more mindful. But I made the rookie mistake of having a goal without metrics and a clear strategy. So, I can’t tell if I was indeed more mindful or not. In this post, I’m sharing some highlights from my 2021, in a random order. I personally find it fascinating to look at these at a later time.&#xA;Family. Thanks to work from home for the entire year, we spent a lot of time together as a family.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open-source: If You Build it Right, They&#39;ll Come</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/11/07/open-source-strategy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/11/07/open-source-strategy/</guid>
      <description>I find open-source to be a rather loaded term; it means different things to different people. For this blog post, I&amp;rsquo;ll imagine there are two kinds of open-source products:&#xA;Company-owned open-source Crowd-owned open-source I&amp;rsquo;m writing this blog post specifically about company-owned open-source products. In a typical company-owned open-source product, the company pays us to develop and maintain the product. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on the Azure Communication Services UI Library that falls into this category.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UI SDK Design Principles</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/10/12/ui-sdk-design-principles/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/10/12/ui-sdk-design-principles/</guid>
      <description>At Microsoft, I’ve been working with my team on a multi-platform UI SDK for Azure Communication Services. We empower developers to build visually delightful communication experiences (chat, audio-video calling, etc.) for everyone. I’ve participated in numerous design discussions on this UI SDK and I realized many of the things I learned here apply to the domain of UI SDKs beyond just the one we are creating. So, this blog post is an attempt to make a list of design principles that developers of UI SDKs can follow to create a bigger impact out of their work.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Onboarding as a New Engineering Manager</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/08/09/onboarding-as-a-new-engineering-manager/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/08/09/onboarding-as-a-new-engineering-manager/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;I promise to take care of you&amp;rdquo; - believe it or not, I spent hours to come up with this message to make a first impression as a newly hired manager at Microsoft. Everyone in my team had more context than me. I was a complete newbie, yet their manager. While I had been a manager for several years, I had never started a new job as a manager. I felt super vulnerable.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Architecture - Topic 6 - Slack and Microsoft Teams</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/06/18/architecture-realtime/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/06/18/architecture-realtime/</guid>
      <description>Most applications have a request-response based single-channel data-flow. In such systems, human or software triggered requests are served by software provided responses. For example, when you make your DuckDuckGo search, you initiate a request and their server produces a response back to you. Realtime multiplayer systems are quite different because the pattern of information flow is more complex, often being a two-way or many-to-many data flow, with strict latency constraints. For example, when you chat with a bunch of friends, or join them for a video call, the data-flow is quite different than when you watch a YouTube video.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Architecture - Topic 5 - MongoDB</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/04/23/architecture-mongodb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/04/23/architecture-mongodb/</guid>
      <description>Continuing on this architecture series of posts. Similar to the post on Redis, this time let&amp;rsquo;s focus on another hugely popular distributed database called MongoDB. If you aren&amp;rsquo;t familiar with MongoDB, it&amp;rsquo;s a distributed database that allows you to store and query humongous amounts of JSON-like data.&#xA;To get an overview of MongoDB and its architecture, you can watch the following YouTube video:&#xA;Of course, you can also download the official architecture guide to learn more.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Architecture - Topic 4 - Redis</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/03/04/architecture-redis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/03/04/architecture-redis/</guid>
      <description>Welcome back to the Software Architecture series. I know at least a few people from my team are following, and that&amp;rsquo;s a great encouragement.&#xA;For today&amp;rsquo;s post, let&amp;rsquo;s focus on learning from a very popular and commonly used open-source project called Redis. To the developers, Redis is a dead simple key-value store with a super simple API as follows:&#xA;$ set today &amp;#39;Thursday&amp;#39; OK $ get today Thursday $ set temp 20 OK $ incr temp 21 $ incrby temp 3 24 $ get temp 24 Of course Redis has more advanced features, but not too many.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can I Have a Career as a Frontend Engineer?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/02/19/frontend-engineering/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/02/19/frontend-engineering/</guid>
      <description>In my current role at Microsoft, I&amp;rsquo;m working on a UI SDK product. I hear this concern from some of my team members. More specifically, here&amp;rsquo;s a paraphrased version of what I hear:&#xA;&amp;ldquo;I talked to my friends in software and they told me it&amp;rsquo;s better to work on the backend or full-stack to have a fast-tracked career.&amp;rdquo;&#xA;First, I do agree that there are generally more full-stack or backend engineering jobs than purely frontend jobs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Architecture - Topic 3: Writing</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/01/17/software-architecture-part-3-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/01/17/software-architecture-part-3-writing/</guid>
      <description>An architect first needs to write for herself, and then for her team. Let me explain a bit.&#xA;An architect takes the trio of requirements, people, and environment, and does her research to design the most delightful system. In her research process, she uses her past experience as well as the experience of others. Even a moderately complex system design involves a lot of trade-offs without clear winners. For example, given that there are tens of different databases one can choose, how can she recommend a specific one?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Drives Me?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/01/16/what-drives-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/01/16/what-drives-me/</guid>
      <description>First, working with good people for a good purpose. Then, moving fast and delivering incrementally. Then, a good business case. And finally, a reasonably modern tech-stack.&#xA;Other things, such as pay, promotion and prestige are important, but it doesn’t drive me like the above.&#xA;This content is suitable for a Twitter post, but putting it here for long term retention. I want to look back after a few years to see how timeless this drivers are for me.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Architecture - Topic 2: People</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/30/software-architecture-part-2-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/30/software-architecture-part-2-people/</guid>
      <description>To be an architect, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to be a leader. And, to be a leader, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to be able to understand people and create an influence on them. So, focusing on the people involved with a system is a pre-requisite for designing systems that delight them.&#xA;Photo credits to Alan O&amp;rsquo;Rourke&#xA;For this topic, I want you to read and internalize the ideas from the book How to Win Friends and Influence People by Dale Carnegie.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Architecture - Topic 1: Delightfulness</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/26/software-artchitecture-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/26/software-artchitecture-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;I want to be an architect&amp;rdquo; - is a common career goal I hear during one:one meetings and annual reviews with my team members. Honestly, I&amp;rsquo;m writing this series of blog posts to bring some clarity and structure into my own thoughts, and hopefully to scale my time. You can even say, I&amp;rsquo;m open-sourcing my mentorship on the topic of software archtecture. My sincere hope is, this series helps my team or anyone who wants to systematically learn and improve their software design skills.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>&#34;you&#39;re unfrogettable&#34;</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/24/you-are-unfrogettable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/24/you-are-unfrogettable/</guid>
      <description>This card is a parting gift from my beloved team. (Catherine, I know you made it)&#xA;This post is dedicated to my team at Cisco. I put a lot of my passion and care into building and being part of a great team during my time at Cisco, eight amazing years between 2012 to 2020. It was the privilege of a lifetime to be able to learn from and mentor an amazing group of people while building a product together.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Tribute to Time Travel APIs in Ruby on Rails</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/07/tribute-to-rails-date-time-great-invisible-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/07/tribute-to-rails-date-time-great-invisible-design/</guid>
      <description>Good design is obvious. Great design is transparent. — Joe Sparano&#xA;Ruby on Rails delighted me all through my career. The community is one with a taste for art, thanks to DHH&amp;rsquo;s ability to write well. He set a high bar and the community also lives up to it. One API that absolutely blows my mind is how delightful it is to work with date and time in Ruby on Rails.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tips for Great Developer Demos</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/28/tips-for-developer-demos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/28/tips-for-developer-demos/</guid>
      <description>Image source: Show and tell - explaining the rain game&#xA;I started my developer career 15 years ago at the onset of agile and Scrum. From my early career, I worked on short sprints where we demoed our work to collect feedback towards the end of each sprint. So, after thousands of demos, I’ve seen enough great ones that I developed a taste for it. I can no longer go back to soulless demos.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Where to Learn: 10 Ways I Do</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/18/where-to-learn/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/18/where-to-learn/</guid>
      <description>When talking to people, I&amp;rsquo;m always interested to know how they learn. This image above shows a view of how I personally learn. Here&amp;rsquo;s some context about the items on the diagram:&#xA;Online-courses: I love O&amp;rsquo;Reilly learning. Their video courses are split into 5 minute lectures. For example, I took their Kotlin course to learn the language. Books: Books are great for curated content, but it takes dedicated time. Most of the time, I have one book that I read.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learn to Get and Give Feedback</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/12/learn-to-get-and-give-feedback/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/12/learn-to-get-and-give-feedback/</guid>
      <description>Photo credits to GotCredit&#xA;Here’s a personal story about getting a feedback. For context, English is my second language. I grew up speaking Bangla as my primary language. I learned reading and writing English in school - grammar first. I had only started speaking English much later in my life, in my mid-twenties. So, I often struggle with the informal form of the language. With this context, here’s an excerpt of a one:one chat conversation at work (from memory):</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My YouTube Playlist for Leadership</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/04/youtube/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/04/youtube/</guid>
      <description>This summer I was interviewing for a new job. This was the first time I was interviewing for an engineering manager role. Soon I realized these interviews were wildly different from interviews for developer roles. During typical developer interviews, I solved coding and system design problems and discussed personal aspirations in behavioral interviews. In contrast, leadership interview qeustions were really open-ended. Honestly, I found it very hard to answer these questions concisely.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Difference Between Managing One Team Vs. Many</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/10/12/managing-one-vs-many-teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/10/12/managing-one-vs-many-teams/</guid>
      <description>Photo credits: Bradley Griffin&#xA;The conductor of an orchestra doesn’t make a sound. He depends for his power on his ability to make others powerful. My job was to awaken possibility in other people. And you know how you find out? You look at their eyes. If their eyes are shining you know you’re doing it. - Benjamin Zander&#xA;Recently, I’ve talked to a few companies as I was going through a job search process after a long time.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Communication Hacks I Learned From Job Interview Feedback</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/10/11/communication-hacks-from-interview-feedback/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/10/11/communication-hacks-from-interview-feedback/</guid>
      <description>Photo credits to UnknownNet Photography&#xA;I’ve been in search of a new job for the past few months. Thanks to my recruiters and interviewers, I’ve received some useful feedback. Many thanks to them for this gift.&#xA;``Needs more energy&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; - This was the most memorable feedback I got. It was from the VP of a company. My interview with him was the last of the five on the same day.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Context</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/09/15/context/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/09/15/context/</guid>
      <description>Image credits to NCinDC&#xA;Context is everything. Due to a context mismatch projects such as exporting democracy, agile transformations, building startups, losing weight, mindfulness or anything you can think of fail to repeat.&#xA;Context is formed by why / what / who / when / where / how, each of these being a critcial part. Most often it&amp;rsquo;s common to focus on the how alone - forgetting the rest of the context while adopting a recipe for success in business.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Change</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/08/31/change/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/08/31/change/</guid>
      <description>Manager&amp;rsquo;s Mind As managers, we have the benefit of view because we have our eyes on longer term goals. To achieve those goals, we often have to introduce a change. For example, we may want to change how a team is formed or what product a team works on based on new business needs or opportunities. So, we put a lot of thought into it and propose our plan to the team hoping the following reaction:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When I Applied KonMari to My Calendar</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/07/17/when-i-applied-kon-mari-to-my-calendar/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/07/17/when-i-applied-kon-mari-to-my-calendar/</guid>
      <description>“I&amp;rsquo;d like to tidy up the entire planet. I would go anywhere if there were something that needs tidying.” - Marie Kondo&#xA;Well, she came to my work calendar in spirit. Let’s start with some backstory.&#xA;When I was developer, my typical day looked like this: one standup meeting and then pretty much the rest of the day in coding. Sometimes I paired up or jumped on a whiteboard session with my coworkers to hash things out.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>People Management and Diagnosing Low Performance</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/05/18/engineering-management-and-diagnosing-low-performance/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/05/18/engineering-management-and-diagnosing-low-performance/</guid>
      <description>Beginning with a story here. Back in 2008, I was a couple of years out of college and working for a software company in Dhaka, Bangladesh. Like many of my classmates from my college, I was studying GRE alongside my job for a PhD admission in a reputable US university. That process being long and uncertain, I also applied for an MBA program at the University of Dhaka as a backup plan.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I Just Love to Read Code</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/02/28/i-just-love-to-read-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/02/28/i-just-love-to-read-code/</guid>
      <description>This week I took a couple of days to focus on my mid-thirties. It got me thinking about what I actually love doing as a hobby. The list is fairly small, walks with the family, soccer, tennis, coffee with friends, reading, writing, car videos, and Netflix.&#xA;Thinking about how I spend my idle time, I realized that I missed two things that I actually love and spend a fair amount of time on: stock markets and reading open-source code.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Working With Me</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/02/08/working-with-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/02/08/working-with-me/</guid>
      <description>Since I commonly work with a diverse group of people, this post is a way for me to broadcast some quick tricks that may help our working relationship. When we work together, let&amp;rsquo;s do this:&#xA;Trust is only earned when it&amp;rsquo;s mutual. Let&amp;rsquo;s work with this shared belief.&#xA;Context is everything. Most importantly, show me why we need to work on something. If the answer isn&amp;rsquo;t clear in your mind, we can work together to build a crisp context.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How About Full-Stack Micro-Services?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/11/17/how-about-full-stack-micro-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/11/17/how-about-full-stack-micro-services/</guid>
      <description>Source: [Audrey on Flickr](https://flic.kr/p/pUW8f9) I think nobody knows how to stitch together an app with full-stack micro-services. I have the following open-questions if you disagree. Of course, if we could send people to moon, we could solve these problems. But the question is, is it worth and should your team solve these problems? Especially, for small teams?&#xA;How to render the UI from tens of independent micro-services into the same web page?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notes from The VoxxedDays Banff, 2019</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/09/23/notes-from-the-voxxeddays-banff/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/09/23/notes-from-the-voxxeddays-banff/</guid>
      <description>Gone are the days when I used to go to a ton of local developer meetups. After Polyglot YYC, this was the second conference I joined this year. This was a 50/50 event for me in terms of like vs. dislike. Here goes my notes:&#xA;Ix-Chel Ruiz presented the keynote to start the day. Her storytelling style reminded me of WWII movies, where a lot of cloudy and gloomy scene keep getting darker and darker, ending with a deep sense of sadness.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What We Learned About Feature Flags in Five Years</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/08/13/what-we-learned-about-feature-flag-in-five-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/08/13/what-we-learned-about-feature-flag-in-five-years/</guid>
      <description>Looking at our git logs from Cisco AMP for Endpoints Console, I see that we introduced feature flags back in January, 2014. The reason I got interested in it is because even after all these years of use, today I had to build a new concept on our feature flag code. If you&amp;rsquo;re already using feature flags or thinking about adding feature flags to your project, this experience report may be helpful.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Software Architecture is all about Ugly Boxes and Lines - My Wishlist</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/08/10/software-architecture-is-all-aboout-ugly-boxes-and-lines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/08/10/software-architecture-is-all-aboout-ugly-boxes-and-lines/</guid>
      <description>In my last post, I claimed software architecture is all talk and no show. When we have a visible one, it&amp;rsquo;s a bunch of poorly drawn boxes and lines. I don&amp;rsquo;t have a problem with boxes or lines, but I do like beautiful drawings.&#xA;Despite many standards, we still mostly use whiteboard drawing of boxes and lines for sharing software design as we build new systems or introduce new team members.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All Talk No Show: Software Architecture</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/08/02/all-talk-no-show-software-architecture/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/08/02/all-talk-no-show-software-architecture/</guid>
      <description>We have a problem with software architecture. Let&amp;rsquo;s face it. Find the architecture diagrams of the products you&amp;rsquo;re working on and answer these questions:&#xA;Did you find it? Does everyone in your team know where to find it? Is it up-to-date? Can you see how this system scales, handles failover, monitors performance, or how it&amp;rsquo;s secured? Can you see how it evolved over time? Can you train a new team-member using this diagram?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Play at Work</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/07/04/play-at-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/07/04/play-at-work/</guid>
      <description>Image source: [Kalvis](https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgz/) &amp;ldquo;I am a mango&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;First, mangoes are in-season, and I still remember the juicy sweetness of the mango I had just the night before. So, when the coach asked each of us to be a fruit, I didn&amp;rsquo;t think twice. One of my coworkers was a kiwi, another one apple, and so on. The idea was to group us by color, then by size. This got us, twenty people in the class, moving and engaged.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Internal Trainings</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/06/27/internal-trainings/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/06/27/internal-trainings/</guid>
      <description>Design Thinking course, Cisco Calgary Office, AB, 2019 One benefit of working at Cisco is access to the many learning and development resources. Our learning and development org arranges hundreds of courses throughout the year. Moreover, we have a reimbursement program for external courses, conferences, books, and subscriptions to online learning programs and publications.&#xA;In the past 6 years, I have immensely benefitted from these resources. Here&amp;rsquo;s a list of the learning resources I&amp;rsquo;ve used.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polyglot YYC 2019: My First Unconference</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/06/05/polyglot-yyc-2019-my-first-unconference/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/06/05/polyglot-yyc-2019-my-first-unconference/</guid>
      <description>Source: Polyglot YYC This weekend I went to Polyglot YYC 2019. It&amp;rsquo;s a gathering of tech people from around Calgary. The event was open to all possible topics, hence the name Polyglot. It was the first unconference style meetup I went to and this post is a summary of my day.&#xA;About the attendees, I don&amp;rsquo;t have the official count, but I imagine there were close to a hundred people.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Micro Design Critic: Microsoft Word vs. Apple Pages</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/05/29/microsoft-word-vs-apple-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/05/29/microsoft-word-vs-apple-pages/</guid>
      <description>Showing a Screenshot of Microsoft Word for Mac and Apple Pages&#xA;This is what you get by default when you open a blank document on both editors. I love that Apple Pages puts a deep focus on the content. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t used it, I&amp;rsquo;d recommend trying it out. I know Microsoft Word has a known face, so you&amp;rsquo;re likely used to all the distractions that sorrounds the content. But, if you can, give Apple Pages a try.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exception Handling Anti-patterns</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/05/23/exception-handling-anti-patterns/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/05/23/exception-handling-anti-patterns/</guid>
      <description>Source: [Henry Burrows](https://www.flickr.com/photos/foilman/2803261256/in/photolist-5gHrUC-5YEVYt-ocZHz7-2bDb3w8-aCGGSo-cB9opW-dUUDRS-6qbnVw-ppkgWu-cYsKjw-4HSS8t-aAJCk5-XBWQ5q-cYsKDA-NNefT4-p8HF-bfJwPB-6SibT9-ubSQL-mvaYX-7uNS7V-473w41-HABo5-5SL6FL-2f4rrkN-SazHLx-2eaMrNW-2eaMsbQ-24J1WkB-24CQREz-24CQR5g-bvyvt7-RvjAiK-6asxLk-9zRJ1e-6zLy6Z-9yuCpf-24FpgMX-95dVq3-hERZkd-4JKe8s-hESYoP-hESYnX-4oPtJ8-6gvogb-5skgvk-4Pu7Hp-8AmdYp-2t55t-24FpgYt) Whenever faced with a production issue, I find exceptions to be an extremely useful information source. A careful look at an exeption has often led to quick discovery of the source of a trouble. On the flip side, I have also faced a lot of chaotic debugging sessions because of poor exception handling. Here, I present the common anti-patterns that I recommend fixing while reviewing pull-requests. Most programmers are already familiar with the mechanics of exception handling.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>“Ah, how good it is to be among people who are reading.”</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/04/11/ah/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/04/11/ah/</guid>
      <description>Rainer Maria Rilke&#xA;All creators take a deep interest in the creations of others. All filmmakers watch a lot of movies, all good writers are also the most prolific readers, all artists can talk at length about the smallest pieces of art they have seen.&#xA;We, software developers, if we want to claim ourselves as the artists of this craft, we must be prolific readers of code. There&amp;rsquo;s been no better time as today.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How am I Developing the People I Support as a People Leader?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/03/26/how-am-i-developing-the-people-i-support-as-a-people-leader/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/03/26/how-am-i-developing-the-people-i-support-as-a-people-leader/</guid>
      <description>After being a people leader at work for the past six years, I’m now going through a phase of introspection. Essentially, I’m trying to understand my own philosophy about people leadership so that I can clearly communicate it to the people that I support.&#xA;My most important realization is, people leadership is all about developing people. What I mean by this is, for everyone I’m supporting, I must carefully build a plan that provides them with the opportunities to stay motivated so that they can thrive.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ruby on Rails: Database Migration and Downtime</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/03/18/ruby-on-rails-database-migration-and-downtime/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/03/18/ruby-on-rails-database-migration-and-downtime/</guid>
      <description>Recently, we had a production outage for a few minutes due a database migration on one of our Ruby on Rails apps. The deployment went fine through a few stages, but the problem only showed up at the last and the largest stage. This is exactly what happened during the deploy process.&#xA;New code was deployed. Restart was pending, so the server was still running old code. Migrations ran. One migration removed a column that was used in the old code, but no longer used in the new code.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What I Learned from Grad School about Innovation?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/01/01/lessons-from-grad-school-how-to-solve-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/01/01/lessons-from-grad-school-how-to-solve-problems/</guid>
      <description>Src: Claudia Dea&#xA;Most problems are solved inefficiently. Innovation follows when a problem is researched first.&#xA;I spent a fair amount of time in grad school. First, sixteen months on my MSc, and then another forty eight months on my PhD program. Also, I worked as a pro software engineer for 20 hours/week during my MSc days and then full-time during the PhD days. It was quite an undertaking, but I survived and now claiming my bragging rights :-)</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Headless CI</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2018/10/10/headless-ci/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2018/10/10/headless-ci/</guid>
      <description>Past few months at work we&amp;rsquo;re trying to revamp our CI infra. This has been a migration from a Jenkins cluster to GoCD. This post is a result of my frustrations with the state of CI in the age of Git/GitHub.&#xA;With Pull Requests, or a form of pre-merge review process, it&amp;rsquo;s common to leverage a few automated checks alongside our human peers to remove potentially breaking changes from being merged into the repo.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The PhD Project</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/10/31/the-phd-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/10/31/the-phd-project/</guid>
      <description>Finally, I defended my PhD thesis yesterday. Family, friends, and colleagues are all sending their wishes, and it feels great to have crossed this milestone.&#xA;To be honest, deep inside, I carry a sad and guilty feeling, which at times overshadows the feeling of acomplishment. This phenomenon is hard to write about, but I wanted to give it a try anyway.&#xA;So, it was 2012. Life was good. I got promoted to Senior Consultant at ThoughtWorks and Shahana got a job almost immediately following the completion of her grad school.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Reference Checks: Don&#39;ts</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/09/07/on-reference-checks-donts/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/09/07/on-reference-checks-donts/</guid>
      <description>Most people eventually come across a time when they&amp;rsquo;d need to provide names of colleagues as references while applying for a new job. The referees are often involved in the last stage of the hiring process, when the employer is generally satisfied that the candidate is a potential hire. At this stage, the employer expects to find a few things:&#xA;Verification of facts. The employer wants to confirm the validity of the information such as the role, responsibilities, and achievements provided by the candidate about their past experience.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>So you want to be a software developer. Where to start?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/02/28/so-you-want-to-be-a-software-developer-where-to-start/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/02/28/so-you-want-to-be-a-software-developer-where-to-start/</guid>
      <description>You didn&amp;rsquo;t go to college to study computer science and you have no background on computer programming. You&amp;rsquo;re not quite happy with your current job area, and looking forward to something more rewarding and exciting. You&amp;rsquo;ve heard software development is generally a good area and often times people without any prior software background can actually get a job. But where do you start?&#xA;First, you&amp;rsquo;re thinking in the right direction, and I can assure you that if you like making things and have a nack for problem-solving, you can learn the skills to become a programmer.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why do you want this new job?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/02/27/why-do-you-want-this-new-job/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/02/27/why-do-you-want-this-new-job/</guid>
      <description>No matter which side of the table you&amp;rsquo;ve sat during interviews, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably heard this question: &amp;lsquo;Why do you want this new job?&amp;rsquo;&#xA;In the recent past, I&amp;rsquo;ve interviewed a few candidates and heard the following answers so far:&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m not learning much on the current job after it&amp;rsquo;s been 2-4 years. I&amp;rsquo;m looking for something that offers better work-life balance. I&amp;rsquo;m not really looking for a job. The recruiters got in touch and I thought I&amp;rsquo;d discuss.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2017 and beyond</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/01/02/2017-and-beyond/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/01/02/2017-and-beyond/</guid>
      <description>2017 will be the year to get closer to my PhD defense, and spending my time with family and dear ones. It means a stricter control on the daily use of social media. That&amp;rsquo;s pretty much it.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;ll sharpen my focus on events and matters that I can influence with the aim to get better at achieving the most within my limited circle of influence. This is a fairly small circle; myself, family, team at work, and a handful of friends.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Annual letter</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2016/12/18/annual-letter-to-myself-and-to-the-www/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2016/12/18/annual-letter-to-myself-and-to-the-www/</guid>
      <description>2016 Highs and lows Baby #2, it&amp;rsquo;s a girl Shera, our little daughter, was born this year. She has been happy, healthy, and an absolute source of joy. Almost hard to believe that we somehow sustained the pregnancy period of my wife, while also running after our active toddler son, Shopoth. Such a pleasure to see the two already reaching for one another, cuddling, giggling, and occasionally fighting.&#xA;Canadian Citizenship, eh!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RailsConf 2015</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/05/08/railsconf-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/05/08/railsconf-2015/</guid>
      <description>I have finally been able to attend a RailsConf, the 2015 edition was my first ever. And I got to say hi to people like @dhh, @wycats, and many more. Thanks Cisco for sponsoring this trip.&#xA;The attendance on the conference was totally amazing, heaven knows how many, but it looked like a couple thousands of rails developers attended the @dhh keynote. And @dhh delivered a good one. Unlike the last year&amp;rsquo;s talk, this year it didn&amp;rsquo;t cause a huge noise because it was mostly about announcing new features of rails to be released with Rails 5.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rails: Please include a JS test runner</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/03/23/rails-please-include-a-js-test-runner/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/03/23/rails-please-include-a-js-test-runner/</guid>
      <description>For an opinionated framework like Ruby on Rails, I expect it to come pre-bundled with a CoffeeScript based test framework and test runner. Here&amp;rsquo;s why:&#xA;Teams don&amp;rsquo;t need to waste time deciding which one to use among the mess of Jasmine, Mocha, Expect, Sinon, Chai, Bower, Grunt, Teaspoon, Npm&amp;hellip; you name it.&#xA;It&amp;rsquo;d work better than what&amp;rsquo;s out there since the Rails team will focus on clean integration with Rails and will have a much larger user base to collect contribution from.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>You Can Haz Automated REST API Documentation</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/01/13/you-can-haz-automated-rest-api-documentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/01/13/you-can-haz-automated-rest-api-documentation/</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s face it, the manual process of documenting REST APIs sucks big time. The process goes like this:&#xA;Craft a cURL request for an API Endpoint. Copy the response. Narrate the API, paste the cURL and response on an editor. Edit the response, describe necessary request and response headers, query parameters etc. Repeat steps 1-4 for each of your tens of Endpoints. Publish the documentation on the web. Repeat these steps for each release.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2015</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/01/02/2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/01/02/2015/</guid>
      <description>This is a much shorter new year post. 2014 was the year of focusing on health, soft-skills, Haskell, social contribution and PhD in addition to typical everyday stuff. Hoping 2015 will be the year of:&#xA;reconnecting with friends and relatives&#xA;perfection&#xA;While Facebook and Twitter make it easy to browse through my friends&amp;rsquo; photos and status updates, I feel quite reluctant to interact on these media. Also, this passive mode of keeping in touch sucks, since my friends are largely unaware of the fact that I still care.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lessons Learned: Entrepreneurship and Innovation Course</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/12/09/lessons-learned-entrepreneurship-and-innovation-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/12/09/lessons-learned-entrepreneurship-and-innovation-course/</guid>
      <description>This fall semester, I signed for the Entrepreneurship and Innovation course (ENTI 781) at the Haskyne Business School of University of Calgary. Wanted to capture my thoughts on this course for my readers here.&#xA;First, the course was unconventional since there are very little academic material to teach entrepreneurship and innovation. The teacher, Olga Petricevic, did a decent job of collecting materials comprising of academic papers, case studies, newspaper articles and YouTube videos as well as bringing in a local entrepreneur for a lecture one day.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s wrong with the default alert rendered by the browser?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/11/20/whats-wrong-with-the-default-alert-rendered-by-the-browser/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/11/20/whats-wrong-with-the-default-alert-rendered-by-the-browser/</guid>
      <description>Browsers have carefully crafted the alert and confirm dialogs for everyone under really simple APIs as follows:&#xA;alert(&amp;#39;Failed to send the email. Check your network connection.&amp;#39;); confirm(&amp;#39;Are you sure you want to delete this email?&amp;#39;); While writing cross-browser JavaScript is not as painful today, custom implementation of these natively supported dialogs seem to be a complete waste of money and time to me. With all the different browsers that we have to support today, including the mobile browsers, it seems a lot of wasted effort in trying to render a custom alert and confirm dialog under any circumstance.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>100 Miles, a 100 Miles...</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/10/31/100-miles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/10/31/100-miles/</guid>
      <description>So, on the 18th of October, 2014, I&amp;rsquo;ve completed my goal of running a 100 miles in 50 days and wanted to share some data for my readers. Enjoy!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>50 Miles!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/10/01/50-miles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/10/01/50-miles/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post about the 100 Miles Challenge, I shared my goal to complete a 100 mile run in 50 days. And I&amp;rsquo;m happy to reach the 50 Miles milestone on day 24, happened this Saturday! 46 Miles to go now, but the target sure looks reachable from here.&#xA;I changed a few things on my end. After running for the first couple of weeks, I found my legs weren&amp;rsquo;t feeling great.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Keeping Things Simple</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/09/25/on-keeping-things-simple/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/09/25/on-keeping-things-simple/</guid>
      <description>Software architecture, or any design for that matter, needs to strike a fine balance between simplicity and power. Sometimes, the design needs to deliberately remove elements that&amp;rsquo;d make life better in some way but also cause a lot of frictions in other ways, ways that may not really impact the designer.&#xA;A few examples to explain this. Client side MVC frameworks on top of a server side MVC framework. Client side URL routing on top of server side URL routing.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monolith vs Microservices</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/09/18/monolith-vs-micro-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/09/18/monolith-vs-micro-services/</guid>
      <description>Microservices are talk of the town these days. I wanted to share my thoughts on microservices based on some experiments that we are running into at our current project.&#xA;SOURCE: https://www.flickr.com/photos/31366276@N03/9327275207/in/photostream/&#xA;Recently, we deployed a microservice for two-step verification feature on one of our projects. This was a strict business requirement, because having a separate server to store your 2nd-factor authorization provides additional security in case the servers hosting your primary factor are compromised.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>100 Miles in 50 Days Challenge</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/09/12/100-miles-in-50-days-challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/09/12/100-miles-in-50-days-challenge/</guid>
      <description>Weightloss is a tough chase. I&amp;rsquo;ve attempted many times and failed.&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo of day 2, when I ran my first 5K in years.&#xA;Last year I decided to change the focus. Instead of aiming for weightloss, I started aiming for a better lifestyle. To some extent, that worked. But I can&amp;rsquo;t say it really made a big difference of any sort.&#xA;I always thought I was a team sport person and hated doing anything only by myself, so much so that, I need a partner even for swimming.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hosting a Hands-on Session: Lessons Learned</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/06/02/hosting-a-hands-on-session-lessons-learned/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/06/02/hosting-a-hands-on-session-lessons-learned/</guid>
      <description>Every year, I wish to run a couple of public speaking sessions/presentations/demos. This year, I had the opportunity to teach a hands-on session at CAMUG and wanted to share some lessons learned with my readers on this blog.&#xA;Thanks Terence for taking this photo.&#xA;Scheduling Breaks Because this was a 3 hour session, and I believe my attention span cannot be stretched beyond 40 mins, the 3 hour session was chunked as follows:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AngularJS: Refresh or Die</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/04/03/angularjs-refresh-or-die/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/04/03/angularjs-refresh-or-die/</guid>
      <description>Just worked on my first AngularJS project at http://loveyyc.info (source code) and wanted to share my thoughts about it while the memory is still fresh. My impression in a one-liner:&#xA;AngularJS needs to rename a lot of things and introduce higher level abstraction&#xA;A great technology only becomes so because people feel happy about it. The happiness for people like me comes from the fact that not only I understand the technology well, but also find it to be easy to use.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Year 2014</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/01/30/the-year-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/01/30/the-year-2014/</guid>
      <description>2013 was an amazing year in many ways for my personal life. To recap, the top story of 2013 was of course the birth of our son, Shopoth. And then, we bought our first house, paid off our car-loan and ended the year with a much needed vacation, that too to Bangladesh where we spent some quality time with the families.&#xA;2013 was my year of learning Haskell. I can&amp;rsquo;t claim to be a seasoned Haskell programmer yet.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Configure Me Not</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/11/03/configure-me-not/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/11/03/configure-me-not/</guid>
      <description>Configuration in software provides a method to build systems that can adapt to different configurations. For example, if a website&amp;rsquo;s language and date/currency formats are configurable, then it can be configured to support multiple languages and regional formats. Configuration makes it possible to deliver such features without needing a log of change in the application source code.&#xA;However, this notion of flexibility that configuration provides can be a trap at times.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing Asset Pipeline to Older Apps?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/10/08/how-to-introduce-asset-pipeline-for-older-apps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/10/08/how-to-introduce-asset-pipeline-for-older-apps/</guid>
      <description>Introducing Asset Pipeline to an old project is quite hard. Most pre-asset pipeline projects used small JavaScript/CSS files that are often scoped to a single page or a part of the application. A typical example is as follows:&#xA;$(function(){ $(&amp;#39;#login&amp;#39;).on(&amp;#39;click&amp;#39;, function(){ var isLoginValid = hasValue($(&amp;#39;#user_name&amp;#39;)) &amp;amp;&amp;amp; hasValue($(&amp;#39;#user_password&amp;#39;)); if(isLoginValid){ $(&amp;#39;#login_errors&amp;#39;).hide(); $(&amp;#39;#login_form&amp;#39;).submit(); } else { $(&amp;#39;#login_errors&amp;#39;).show(); return false; } }); }); Now, within the scope of the login page this code executes just fine.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Career choices: Should I take this job?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/09/19/career-choices-should-i-take-this-job/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/09/19/career-choices-should-i-take-this-job/</guid>
      <description>I get intimidated by this question, &amp;ldquo;Should I take this job?&amp;rdquo;&#xA;Growing up, my dad had a huge influence on my upbringing. He had a government job and it was the only job he ever had (retired in 2012). However, my generation Y seems somewhat lucky to be able to pick and choose a job, once every couple years or so. And every time I feel like it&amp;rsquo;s time to start looking around for that next job, I get intimidated by this question.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Will You Put That Cell Phone Away?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/08/27/will-you-put-that-cell-phone-away/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/08/27/will-you-put-that-cell-phone-away/</guid>
      <description>I know it&amp;rsquo;s your phone and you can do anything you want. But may be it&amp;rsquo;s worth holding back at times. There&amp;rsquo;s more to life than our screens.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m leaving it off the hand, off the table and off the bed, in silent mode, all day long. I&amp;rsquo;m asking for permission to use it if I have to while I&amp;rsquo;m with others. Instead of spending the time with the screens, it&amp;rsquo;s been very rewarding to play with my little son, with all the attention on him.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithms Need Better UI</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/08/12/algorithms-need-better-ui/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/08/12/algorithms-need-better-ui/</guid>
      <description>Since 2006, as I became a professional software engineer, I spent a fair amount of time reading books and online articles about software. Most topics were around Object Orientation, Web technologies, Software design, Testing, Automation, Agile and Lean, etc. Last year, I decided to take a break from such topics on purpose. So, I cleared all my RSS subscriptions.&#xA;Instead, I thought I would revisit some of the algorithms that I learned during my undergraduate courses.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AngularJS is Very Productive, and Cool too!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/06/14/angularjs-is-very-productive-and-cool/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/06/14/angularjs-is-very-productive-and-cool/</guid>
      <description>It has a very steep learning curve, but yields a superb productivity boost once you&amp;rsquo;ve learned it. Check out my demo of the wizard that we&amp;rsquo;ll discuss next.&#xA;AngularJS works by extending HTML to produce declarative UI code and eliminating the need for a lot of boilerplate code. For example, the mental model of a wizard can be expressed using the following HTML:&#xA;&amp;lt;wizard title=&amp;#34;Flight Search&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;step title=&amp;#34;Search&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/step&amp;gt; &amp;lt;step title=&amp;#34;Select a flight&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/step&amp;gt; &amp;lt;step title=&amp;#34;Select a return flight&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/step&amp;gt; &amp;lt;step title=&amp;#34;Checkout&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/step&amp;gt; &amp;lt;step title=&amp;#34;Confirm purchase&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/step&amp;gt; &amp;lt;step title=&amp;#34;Receipt&amp;#34;&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/step&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/wizard&amp;gt; With AngularJS, one can write exactly this markup with the help of two custom directives, widget and step.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Released streamy_csv gem</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/05/10/released-streamy-csv-gem/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/05/10/released-streamy-csv-gem/</guid>
      <description>Following the previous post, I decided to spin off a little ruby gem for you folks. Get streamy_csv, and write only your application code while it&amp;rsquo;ll do the boilerplate work for you.&#xA;In a nutshell, with this gem in your application, all you need to do is this:&#xA;Class ExportsController def index stream_csv(&amp;#39;data.csv&amp;#39;, MyModel.header_row) do |rows| MyModel.find_each do |my_model| rows &amp;lt;&amp;lt; my_model.to_csv_row end end end end Find more at https://github.com/smsohan/streamy_csv</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generating and Streaming Potentially Large CSV files using Ruby on Rails</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/05/09/genereating-and-streaming-potentially-large-csv-files-using-ruby-on-rails/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/05/09/genereating-and-streaming-potentially-large-csv-files-using-ruby-on-rails/</guid>
      <description>Most applications I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on at some point required that &amp;lsquo;Export&amp;rsquo; feature so people would be able to play with the data using the familiar Excel interface. I&amp;rsquo;m sharing some code here from a recent work that did the following:&#xA;Generate a CSV file for download with up to 100,000 rows in it. Since the contents of the file depends on some dynamic parameters, and the underlying data is changing all the time, the file must be generated live.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simplicity and Client-Side MVC</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/05/07/simplicity-and-client-side-mvc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/05/07/simplicity-and-client-side-mvc/</guid>
      <description>After spending about 6 months on this new project using BackboneJS, and spending some hours learning AngularJS and EmberJS, my realization at this point is:&#xA;Use Client-Side MVC very Selectively.&#xA;Sometimes on a single page of your app, you need to offer a lot of interactions, each scoped to a small part of the page only. In such cases Client-Side MVC offers some neat features. I&amp;rsquo;ll try to share my perspective with some concrete examples where I&amp;rsquo;d say yes/no to Client-Side MVC.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MicroOptimization Trap</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/30/microoptimization-trap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/30/microoptimization-trap/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, couple of my friends and I were discussing about a CoffeeScript topic. In short, given the following code in CoffeeScript:&#xA;class Cat type: -&amp;gt; &amp;#39;cat&amp;#39; meow: -&amp;gt; &amp;#39;meow meow mee..ow&amp;#39; The compiler produces this in JavaScript:&#xA;var Cat; Cat = (function() { function Cat() {} Cat.prototype.type = function() { return &amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;; }; Cat.prototype.meow = function() { return &amp;#39;meow meow mee..ow&amp;#39;; }; return Cat; })(); As you see here, the prototype method definitions use the prefix Cat.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unconventional Conventions</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/19/unconventional-conventions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/19/unconventional-conventions/</guid>
      <description>JavaScript has been reborn, thanks to jQuery to begin this epic and wonderful march. These days, we have a huge influx of micro to macro frameworks, all providing some well curated set of features. Every now and then I try to get a glimpse of the new and hot stuff so when time comes, I can make an informed decision on what to use and why.&#xA;This post is about my recent attempt at learning AngularJS and EmberJS.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Call me Sohan and Ask-Me-Not about S M</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/05/call-me-sohan-and-ask-me-not-about-sm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/05/call-me-sohan-and-ask-me-not-about-sm/</guid>
      <description>I have heard this question n times, where n tends to the number of days since June 2006, as I started working with the people from North America:&#xA;Should I call you S M?&#xA;Well, I&amp;rsquo;m from Bangladesh and even today, we don&amp;rsquo;t really have a first and last name, instead what we have is, a full name and a nick name. My full name is, S M Sohan, and my nick name is Sohan.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementation Challenges with a Multi-Tenant/SaaS Database</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/04/implementation-challenges-with-with-a-saas-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/04/implementation-challenges-with-with-a-saas-database/</guid>
      <description>{% img right http://farm1.staticflickr.com/21/26445881_7c69777b7b.jpg 500 353 &amp;lsquo;Photo credits to corydalus&amp;rsquo; &amp;lsquo;climbing&amp;rsquo;%}&#xA;This 2006 MSDN article points out some key aspects of designing a multi-tenant database for SaaS applications. As you can read in the article, SaaS databases need to pick one of the following three configurations:&#xA;separate databases shared database, separate schema and shared database, shared schema. A number of factors including economic, security, skillset, etc. contribute to the selection of the best suitable configuration.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interesting User Interaction Data on Dashboard Widgets</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/02/interesting-user-interaction-data-on-dashboard-widgets/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/02/interesting-user-interaction-data-on-dashboard-widgets/</guid>
      <description>At SourceFire, among other things, we build a cloud based Advanced Malware Protection software. As security products go, we collect a huge amount of data about events that happen on the user devices so we can identify and potentially quarantine malicuous events. Security in itself is a big specialized domain, but this post is about a dashboard that we serve as the main point of entry into the big data that we collect from enterprises and consumers.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MvcMailer and Open Source Happiness</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/03/18/mvcmailer-and-open-source-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/03/18/mvcmailer-and-open-source-happiness/</guid>
      <description>MvcMailer makes me happy as a developer.&#xA;I find an immense amount of happiness everytime I check the Nuget page of MvcMailer. It&amp;rsquo;s so refreshing to see the download count going up (42,427 total downloads as I write), receiving feedback, praises and even the complains.&#xA;The idea of MvcMailer came from trying to bring some of the amazing Ruby on Rails ActionMailer features to ASP.NET MVC developers. It was well accepted since the very beginning and I hope is still helping people.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solution Architecting Using Queues?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/03/07/solution-architecting/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/03/07/solution-architecting/</guid>
      <description>When building a bunch of applications that need to interact with each other, Queues or Message Oriented Middleware services offer some very useful features. To name a few, you get features like a) Guaranteed message delivery, b) routing, c) throttling, etc., for free. Tools like ActiveMQ, RabbitMQ, MSMQ, JMS servers are tuned and time tested to handle such requirements robustly. I&amp;rsquo;ve had good experience with these tools for the happy paths.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random Data in Tests</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/02/27/random-data-in-tests/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/02/27/random-data-in-tests/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; are evil if you expect the randomizer to give you unique values on each call.&#xA;Here&amp;rsquo;s an example:&#xA;before(:each) do @user_1 = User.create!(email: &amp;#34;email-#{Random.rand(1000)}@example.com&amp;#34;) # the following will fail intermittently if you have a unique validation on User#email @user_2 = User.create!(email: &amp;#34;email-#{Random.rand(1000)}@example.com&amp;#34;) end It&amp;rsquo;s a timebomb, use it, it will haunt you later. Be sane, stop using random numbers in tests like this.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practical API Design Challenges for Client Side MVC</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/02/25/practial-challenges-with-client-side-mvc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/02/25/practial-challenges-with-client-side-mvc/</guid>
      <description>This following list is probably a subset of a bigger one, but I&amp;rsquo;ve composed it based on my experience using BackboneJS + Rails on the current project at work. So, here goes the list:&#xA;###Designing Granularity of the API###&#xA;Using RESTful API, it makes sense to have separate API methods to repesent each type of resource. However, to construct a meaninful UI for the end user, often time we need to represent multiple resources on the same screen.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are ActiveRecord Callbacks Any Good?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/02/07/activerecord-callbacks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/02/07/activerecord-callbacks/</guid>
      <description>Wanted to share my thoughts on ActiveRecord Callbacks. I&amp;rsquo;d like to know your thoughts if you disagree. Please use the comments.&#xA;Only use them when the behavior is must have under all situations, including your tests. For example, we know email addresses are case-insensitive. So no matter what, we may always want to store a lower cased version in the db. #Good class User &amp;lt; ActiveRecord::Base before_save :downcase_email def downcase_email email.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rejecting Because It Didn&#39;t Work Last Time</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/01/24/rejecting-because-it-didnt-work-last-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/01/24/rejecting-because-it-didnt-work-last-time/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; is as right as &amp;ldquo;the weather will be bad today because it wasn&amp;rsquo;t any good yesterday&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On ActiveRecord Query Enhancers</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/01/21/on-activerecord-query-enhancers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/01/21/on-activerecord-query-enhancers/</guid>
      <description>The question is, should we use the third-party ActiveRecord Query Enhancers like SearchLogic/Squeel/MetaSearch?&#xA;Quoting from Squeel&amp;rsquo;s Github README page,&#xA;Squeel lets you rewrite... Article.where [&amp;#39;created_at &amp;gt;= ?&amp;#39;, 2.weeks.ago] ...as... Article.where{created_at &amp;gt;= 2.weeks.ago} This is a good thing. If you don&amp;#39;t agree, Squeel might not be for you. At work, we are migrating a Rails 3.0 project into Rails 3.2. We used MetaSearch in the project quite extensively and now discussing if using Squeel (successor of MetaSearch for newer Rails versions) would be a good decision.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MongoDB is Abusing JSON!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/01/17/abusing-json/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/01/17/abusing-json/</guid>
      <description>I find the MongoDB API is abusing JSON in a really bad way. JSON is probably a good format for storing the documents in MongoDB, but using JSON for it&amp;rsquo;s weird API is simply a terrible idea. Here&amp;rsquo;s an example from the SQL to Aggregation Framework Mapping Chart&#xA;db.orders.aggregate( [ { $group: { _id: { cust_id: &amp;#34;$cust_id&amp;#34;, ord_date: &amp;#34;$ord_date&amp;#34; }, total: { $sum: &amp;#34;$price&amp;#34; } } }, { $match: { total: { $gt: 250 } } } ] ) I find the UI of this query to be distasteful at the best.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Persistence</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/01/08/hybrid-persistence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/01/08/hybrid-persistence/</guid>
      <description>Often times the business requirements demand for database features that aren&amp;rsquo;t easily achievable using a single type of database. And now we have quite a few options to choose from, for example Key Value stores, Document databases, Relational databases etc, each providing some mutually exclusive features from the rest. So, it can be tempting to introduce multiple databases to rip the benefits of each.&#xA;But, it comes with a few gotchas that are worth knowing.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How much to validate?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/12/14/how-much-to-validate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/12/14/how-much-to-validate/</guid>
      <description>Input validation is often required to safe guard against inappropriate use. For example, consider the following API:&#xA;class TransfersController def create() from_account_id, to_account_id, amount = params[:from_account_id], params[:to_account_id], params[:amount] from_account = Account.find(from_account_id) to_account = Account.find(to_account_id) @transfer = Transfer.create!(from_account, to_account, amount) redirect_to @transfer end end In this case, the API is expecting a from_account_id which we know, can be easily exploited unless a validation is performed on the server. Say, a simple validation would do this:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Programming Language Should I Learn in 2013?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/12/12/what-programming-language-should-i-learn-in-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/12/12/what-programming-language-should-i-learn-in-2013/</guid>
      <description>I like the idea of learning one new programming language every year. This is also mentioned at The Pragmatic Programmer Book. I&amp;rsquo;m now looking for a new language to learn.&#xA;In 2011, I learned F#, my first functional programming language experience. It&amp;rsquo;s a really nice language, especially if you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with the .Net class library and the windows development echo system in general. This was really fun, learned the basic concepts and building blocks of functional languages.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Myth of One Assert Per Test</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/12/06/the-myth-of-one-assert-per-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/12/06/the-myth-of-one-assert-per-test/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR; It&amp;rsquo;s not one assert per test, rather one logical path per test.&#xA;I find this to be a classical example of how an inappropriate choice of terminology leads to huge confusion. In trying to find the original source of the &amp;ldquo;one assertion per test&amp;rdquo; quote, google came back only with a bunch of confused blog entries :(&#xA;Without much ranting, lets see a code example to start with:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Readable Unit Tests</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/11/28/readable-unit-tests/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/11/28/readable-unit-tests/</guid>
      <description>From my experience with writing/reading unit tests for years, here&amp;rsquo;s a little guideline to keep &amp;rsquo;em readable:&#xA;A unit test needs to fit entirely (including setups) on a screen without scrolling. It is OK to have a little bit of duplication in unit tests for readability. Avoid nesting of contexts beyond 2 levels. Instead, use methods to setup and flatten. Do not use if/else/loops in a unit test. If your test needs too much setup/mocking/stubbing, time to refactor the code.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unit Testing and Sleep</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/11/27/unit-testing-asynchronous-side-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/11/27/unit-testing-asynchronous-side-effects/</guid>
      <description>If your unit test code needs a sleep, its time to refactor it. Ideally, you&amp;rsquo;d only need to stub/mock the asynchronous call instead of introducing arbitrary sleeps in the test code, because they will eventually fail. Moreover, until it fails, it will slow down your test runner.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seed Data in a Rails Project</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/11/23/seed-data-in-a-rails-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/11/23/seed-data-in-a-rails-project/</guid>
      <description>Most applications I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on required some kind of seed data. For example, I&amp;rsquo;ve used seed data to create a super admin user so the site can actually be used upon a fresh install. Some other common cases include things like, list of credit card types, names of countries/states etc. This post is about some ideas to manage thsese seed data in a Ruby on Rails project.&#xA;Where to put the seed data?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ORM or Not?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/11/06/orm-or-not/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/11/06/orm-or-not/</guid>
      <description>Yes to ORM, No to custom queries. Here&amp;rsquo;s a bullet list:&#xA;You&amp;rsquo;d probably end up writing your own ORM anyway. Doing so, you&amp;rsquo;d spend a lot of money writing library level code instead of your business logic. The time tested ones are likely to be better than yours. Beware, you&amp;rsquo;d have to figure out some complex issues: connection pooling, concurrency/locking, caching, transactions, updates, versioning, documentation etc. If you find yourself ORM is falling short of what you need, you&amp;rsquo;re either presenting information overload or using a transactional database as a reporting store.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development Environments and Dependency Hell</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/10/25/development-environments-and-dependencies-hell/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/10/25/development-environments-and-dependencies-hell/</guid>
      <description>It used to be pretty straight forward to get up and running with a Rails app. You&amp;rsquo;d expect something like the following:&#xA;git clone git@blah/blah.git cd blah bundle rake db:migrate rails s If the project is using rvm and bundler, the ruby versions and gem depdendencies are all taken care of. So far life is good this way.&#xA;But it starts getting complicated. For example, your project probably uses MySQL and no matter what, I can&amp;rsquo;t remeber all the c libraries that are pre-requisites for the mysql2 gem to actually install successfully.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joined Sourcefire</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/10/22/joined-sourcefire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/10/22/joined-sourcefire/</guid>
      <description>Hello Dear Readers:&#xA;I just wanted to inform you that I&amp;rsquo;ve joined Sourcefire this morning as a Principal Software Engineer. My primary responsibility will be helping my team with Ruby on Rails and Web technology related expertise. I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to this new role.&#xA;ThoughtWorks was a wonderful experience. In the last couple of years with ThoughtWorks, I have worked on 4 different projects, for 4 different clients and business domains from 4 different cities in North America.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pair Programming vs. Code Reviews</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/10/22/pairing-vs-code-reviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/10/22/pairing-vs-code-reviews/</guid>
      <description>Photo credits to http://womendiving.blogspot.ca/2012/08/2012-olympic-games-10m-synchronized.html&#xA;Pair programming is like synchronized swimming. You do it together, you win it together. You try to improve your chances by helping your partner, and vice verca. Even if you lose, its highly likely you&amp;rsquo;ve improved simply by being together sharing a united goal.&#xA;Code review can be fun and really useful too. But deep deep care needs to be taken to ensure it remains same in spirit, that is, the unified shared goal.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Database Design: Sorting by Concepts on Nullable Fields</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/10/11/database-design-sorting-by-computed-fields/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/10/11/database-design-sorting-by-computed-fields/</guid>
      <description>In a recent project, we had this requirement to sort a list of items by a concept that is absent in the database schema, but can be derived from other fields. To make it easy to understand, let&amp;rsquo;s build an example, simple enough to isolate the topic of interest.&#xA;Let&amp;rsquo;s say we have a list of locations, stored in a database table as follows:&#xA;Locations (location_id (primary key), province_id (NULL), city_id (NOT NULL)) And say, we want to present a list of locations sorted by &amp;ldquo;address&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MvcMailer new API</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/10/02/mvcmailer-new-api/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/10/02/mvcmailer-new-api/</guid>
      <description>With the help of @TylerMercier, and many active users of MvcMailer, we have just released the new API for MvcMailer. This is a summary post capturing the work and lessons learned in the process.&#xA;The bulk of the work has been done on removing hard dependencies on dll files for 3rd party libraries in favor of NuGet packages. For example, we used NUnit, for running our tests. Instead of referencing the dlls directly, we are now using the NuGet package.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LoveJS Presentation at CAMUG</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/09/13/lovejs-presentation-at-camug/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/09/13/lovejs-presentation-at-camug/</guid>
      <description>I paired with @TylerMercier as we did a little hands-on demo on writing testable and OO JavaScript.&#xA;This was mostly based on our pairing experience on the current project, but also had things that we learned from our previous web projects. I wanted to share some of the highlights of this session with my readers on this blog:&#xA;From experience, I have seen a few charactersitics that make JavaScript coding a real fun.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deploying a Java Application Using Capistrano</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/08/07/deploying-a-java-application-using-capistrano/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/08/07/deploying-a-java-application-using-capistrano/</guid>
      <description>In our current project, we have a little Java Bridge, that reads JMS messages from an enterprise service bus (ESB) and pipes it to an ActiveMQ topic. This had to be written in Java, or some flavor of it like JRuby/Scala, because the ESB only allows their signed client libraries to interact with their API.&#xA;Since, we were already using Capistrano to deploy our Rails/Nginx app, we wanted to leverage the same tool for deploying the Java Bridge.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design of a MongoDB Analytics Database</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/08/05/design-of-a-mongodb-analytics-database/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/08/05/design-of-a-mongodb-analytics-database/</guid>
      <description>We built a MongoDB based realtime analytics solution and learned a few things in the process. I would like to share some of our learnings in this post.&#xA;When tasked to find a good database for holding realtime analytics data, I was searching through the wisdom of internet to come up with a good choice. At a high level, the database needed to deliver the following:&#xA;Atomic counters so that events could be counted fast.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deploying to TV Screens</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/07/28/deploying-to-tv-screens/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/07/28/deploying-to-tv-screens/</guid>
      <description>Off late, I am working on a project to render real time business data with interesting visualizations, so people can feel the pulse of the business. For the last couple of months, I have been planning to write a detailed post about it. But after a few false starts, I am finally settling on smaller posts, telling a small part of the story each time.&#xA;So, have you ever worked on a web application that is primarily viewed through 55&amp;quot;+ 1080p TV screens?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Take on Client-Side MVC</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/03/30/my-take-on-client-side-mvc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/03/30/my-take-on-client-side-mvc/</guid>
      <description>I just rolled off my last project this Wednesday. It was a great team, worked on some cutting edge technologies, mobile web, HTML5, mongo and some other fun stuff. Now that I got two &#34;beach&#34; days before jumping on to the next gig, I spent some time trying out Backbonejs to knockout one item from the long list of to-dos. This post is about my initial take on client side MVC, solely based on these two days with Backbonejs.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are You Still Parsing HTML Element Ids?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/01/22/are-you-still-parsing-html-element-ids/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/01/22/are-you-still-parsing-html-element-ids/</guid>
      <description>To render a list, often times we use repeated HTML elements with a similar template. For example, the search results in ebay.com is a list of divs, each containing different data in the same template. In a server side, this rendering code is somewhat similar to this:&#xA;If you noticed, a product with it&#39;s database id = 123 will be rendered inside a div with id=&#34;product_123&#34;, and similarly div id=&#34;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Object Versioning is an Open Design Problem</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/01/17/object-versioning-is-open-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/01/17/object-versioning-is-open-design/</guid>
      <description>This unsolvable maze is a local food from Bangladesh, known as Jilapi&#xA;Photo credits to&amp;nbsp;udvranto pothikObject Versioning is often required by a business rule, for example, to maintain an audit trail or to be able to revert to a previous version, etc. This is the 3rd time in my career where this Object Versioning requirement made me think like -&#xA;There&#39;s gotta be an easier solution!&amp;nbsp;But, I am yet to find one.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Care Driven Development: Javascript</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/11/20/care-driven-development-javascript/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/11/20/care-driven-development-javascript/</guid>
      <description>There is * Driven Development, where they listed &#34;all possible thing&#34; driven development and dedicated a whole website to it! Well, I am adding one more to the list, &#34;Care Driven Development&#34;, with an emphasis to Javascript coding.&#xA;Javascript coding, do you care enough?CSS is the most hairy spagetti piece of almost any web project. And its not leading by a far distance to it&#39;s first cousin; Javascript. But, the good thing is, it just takes a little care to clean the bush out of Javascript and make it pretty.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enterprise Software Projects: oh, yeah!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/11/18/enterprise-software-projects-oh-yeah/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/11/18/enterprise-software-projects-oh-yeah/</guid>
      <description>I just rolled off my first ever enterprise software project couple of weeks ago. After staying six months on the project and while the memory is still fresh, I thought I would write a retrospect on the project and on my role.&#xA;The program is rather big, I guess it had ~300 people for the last couple or so years. I joined late for the program. So, by the time I went there, a massive amount of work has already been done, meaning a huge learning curve for me.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aligning an HTML DIV Inside Another One</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/11/13/aligning-html-div-inside-another-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/11/13/aligning-html-div-inside-another-one/</guid>
      <description>Across different projects, I have found people taking CSS shortcuts for translating the Photoshopped design templates into HTML. Back in the days, layout used to be all Table based and it was kind of straight forward to fit everything into grid cells. However, with CSS styling the extra flexibility to put elements in any arbitrary layout came extra responsibility - to make sure things still align nicely while being fluid to accommodate different screen resolutions and form factors.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using instanceof is mostly a Code Smell</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/11/01/using-instanceof-is-mostly-code-smell/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/11/01/using-instanceof-is-mostly-code-smell/</guid>
      <description>When using static programming languages such as Java, often time I have seen people writing methods that accept Object as a parameter. These methods typically don&#39;t really work on any Object, but works with multiple types of classes that don&#39;t have any common base class. Here&#39;s an example of such a method:&#xA;As you can see in this example, the process method actually expects one of CleanFloor or LaunchRocket instances.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nightly Build is a Warning (or Horror)</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/10/04/nightly-build-is-warning-or-horror/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/10/04/nightly-build-is-warning-or-horror/</guid>
      <description>Photo credits:&amp;nbsp;insidethemagic&#xA;I think, Nightly build is an anti-pattern for Continuous Integration. If you are integrating continuously, then you shouldn&#39;t need a nightly build, that would be too discrete :(&#xA;If you already have a per-commit continuous integration setup, you shouldn&#39;t need the so called nightly build unless there&#39;s something bad about the code.&#xA;Often times, builds taking &amp;gt;10 minutes are put in the bucket of nightly builds.&#xA;Some people put batch processing related tests under such nightly builds.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Perils of Soft Delete</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/09/28/perils-of-soft-delete/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/09/28/perils-of-soft-delete/</guid>
      <description>Often times, applications cannot get rid of the database records for business rules. For example, if you are a cable TV provider, you might have a customer calling you to stop the National Geographic Channel subscription from next month.&amp;nbsp;Ideally you would like to delete this record, but you can&#39;t do it until the effective date:( If you delete it, the next invoice will not be able to charge for this channel, although it&#39;s still being used.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hardcoded URLs in Javascript are too Slippery</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/09/23/hardcoded-urls-in-javascript-are-too/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/09/23/hardcoded-urls-in-javascript-are-too/</guid>
      <description>Photo credits to&amp;nbsp;Esteban Cavrico&#xA;I was working on a web project that lets you delete some records using Ajax. The following is just an example, but you might be familiar with a similar code already:&#xA;This code used to work when the DELETE endpoint was indeed under &#39;/blog/posts&#39;. However, at some point a developer wants to remove the &#39;/blog&#39; from all the endpoints to put them directly under &#39;/posts&#39;! You can see, in such cases it is very hard to catch the bug that would be caused by the faulty JS code.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excess of Private Methods is a Code Smell</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/09/20/code-smell-private-vs-public-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/09/20/code-smell-private-vs-public-method/</guid>
      <description>Private methods, when used meaningfully, are a great tool for writing beautiful object oriented code. But as many other things in life, excess of private methods is bad, too!&#xA;In my opinion, we use private methods to:&#xA;1. &amp;nbsp;isolate a block of code to be reused inside the class.&#xA;2. &amp;nbsp;extract code from another method for code readability.&#xA;Now, taking these two use cases in mind, here&#39;s an easy conclusion:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Extend a Ruby Module?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/09/16/how-to-extend-ruby-module/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/09/16/how-to-extend-ruby-module/</guid>
      <description>Modules in Ruby are like classes with a few important differences. One of the differences is, a module cannot inherit from another module using the same syntax as class inheritance. However, its pretty easy to inherit a module&#39;s method into another module, by just using the include ModuleToInclude syntax. Here&#39;s an example if you are looking for one:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quiz: C# Async and Await. What is the Output of this Code?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/09/16/quiz-c-async-and-await-what-is-output/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/09/16/quiz-c-async-and-await-what-is-output/</guid>
      <description>C# 5.0 (CTP version at this point) has support for async and await to allow clean implementation of non-blocking IO using a task-continuation model. I was just playing with it and here&#39;s the sample code to tease your brain. Tell me what is the output of this program?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Should You Unit Test Interaction with Static Methods?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/08/15/should-you-unit-test-interaction-with/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/08/15/should-you-unit-test-interaction-with/</guid>
      <description>No. You should not. Here&#39;s an example:&#xA;If you are somehow mocking this static method, you are potentially making it dangerous for other places where this static method is used. Eventually, this will create red test results that are hard to find and make your tests dependent on each other.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to list all classes that include a module?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/08/12/how-to-list-all-classes-that-include/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/08/12/how-to-list-all-classes-that-include/</guid>
      <description> Here&#39;s the code: </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Should you unit test methods with a lot of mocking?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/08/09/should-you-unit-test-methods-with-lot/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/08/09/should-you-unit-test-methods-with-lot/</guid>
      <description>Well, anytime you have a lot of mocking, it is probably a smell. Particularly, a first smell is violation of the law of demeter. However, we were having discussion about whether or not we should write unit test for something like the following example:&#xA;As you can see, this method actually does a quite important task. It invokes the search method with specific parameters that will determine your search results.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ruby present? Method</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/08/05/ruby-present-method-with-unless/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/08/05/ruby-present-method-with-unless/</guid>
      <description>Ruby has a nice little keyword called unless, that checks the opposite of if. So, you are probably used to a code like this:&#xA;return customer.first_name unless customer.nil?&#xA;If you haven&#39;t used present? before, you can in fact turn the above unless into a more familiar and easy to understand if statement:&#xA;return customer.first_name if customer.present?&#xA;So, in most cases when you are using unless with a negative condition, you can use present?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructors Are Methods, too!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/07/26/should-you-write-unit-tests-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/07/26/should-you-write-unit-tests-for/</guid>
      <description>Yes, if your constructor does something meaningful. This is just like another method and should be treated equally for unit testsing purpose. Here&#39;s an example that should need unit test:&#xA;It looks simple, so testing it should be simple, too. I would only skip the default constuctors, as long as they don&#39;t do anything interesting. Comments Alexander Beletsky Sure, the constructors are methods too.. but they should not do anything more except internal initialization.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Annoy Your Customers? Learn from GoDaddy Account Status Email</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/07/22/how-to-annoy-your-customer-learn-from/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/07/22/how-to-annoy-your-customer-learn-from/</guid>
      <description>Just looking at this screenshot alone, what do you think it is?I have a few domains registered with GoDaddy. I went with them, because at that time, I didn&#39;t know of another renowned provider. But they have always been the best of producing the most confusing ever user interface. The account status email is one step ahead in that same direction.&#xA;This is how it starts:&#xA;At the top right corner, it says July 2011, in grayed out font!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Avoid Duplication in Config Files</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/07/11/avoid-duplication-in-config-files/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/07/11/avoid-duplication-in-config-files/</guid>
      <description>Any kind of configuration file, be it an ugly xml file or a prettier yml or properties file, its been a source of frustration to me. Here&#39;s a list of few such pain points:&#xA;There are two config keys that point to the same value. e.g. db_username=master, data_source_user=masterThere are two config keys for urls that point to the same domain, but different paths. e.g. market.com/cameras and market.com/undiesConfig entries with placeholders.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Not To Provide Feedback When Doing Code Review</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/06/25/how-not-to-provide-feedback-when-doing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/06/25/how-not-to-provide-feedback-when-doing/</guid>
      <description>Code review, as any other review process, can often be an attack on someone&#39;s ego and incite anger and frustration. Being both on sending and receiving end of such code reviews for years, I have learned a few how-not-to-do-it, or as one might say, anti-patterns of providing code review feedback. Let me know if you agree/disagree with me on the following:&#xA;You are always reviewing Adam&#39;s code while Adam is never reviewing yours.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Service API and Exceptions</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/06/22/service-api-and-exceptions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/06/22/service-api-and-exceptions/</guid>
      <description>Too often I see I am using a REST/SOAP API to talk to a third party system that frustrates me because of poor error messaging. Here&#39;s an example to illustrate a typical frustration:&#xA;Call: city_service.update_residence_address(city_dueler, new_address)&#xA;Response: &amp;lt;status&amp;gt;Failed&amp;lt;/status&amp;gt;&amp;lt;error&amp;gt;Invalid address&amp;lt;/error&amp;gt;&#xA;But the address just seems right to me. So, I need to know specific reason about why the address is wrong. The error message leaves this critical detail. What happens next is, I look for the log files created by the city_service, conceptually supposed to be a third party hosted service.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NuGet - Why Should You Care?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/03/17/nuget-why-should-you-care/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/03/17/nuget-why-should-you-care/</guid>
      <description>Traditionally the .NET community, or more appropriately the users of .NET framework relied on products from Microsoft - so, in a product stack you are likely to see almost everything coming from Microsoft. However, some community contribution made its way into the main stream - for example, NUnit or Log4Net. But you can literally count the number of such main stream non-Microsoft products in your development stacks with your fingers (sparing a few)!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My 2011 Q1 developer roadmap</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/03/14/my-2011-q1-developer-roadmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/03/14/my-2011-q1-developer-roadmap/</guid>
      <description>For me, 2011 Q1 has so far been a good exposure to new techniques, tools, articles and books, thanks to ThoughtWorks book allowance! However, if you are interested, here&#39;s what&#39;s keeping me busy:&#xA;User Experience: I find a good user experience is THE thing that you want in anything you design, and if you are writing a software, its even more important. After I read a few books, I have a feeling that its not just a common sense approach, it takes some education and a deep care to produce something usable.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MvcMailer 1.0 Released</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/03/07/mvcmailer-10-released/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/03/07/mvcmailer-10-released/</guid>
      <description> Just released MvcMailer 1.0 as promised in my previous post.&amp;nbsp;Download your copy using the following:&#xA;Install-Package MvcMailerOf course, you will find a comprehensive tutorial at: this github wiki page. </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Whats Coming in MvcMailer NuGet 1.0?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/03/04/whats-coming-in-mvcmailer-nuget-10/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/03/04/whats-coming-in-mvcmailer-nuget-10/</guid>
      <description>Thanks to 365+ downloads of the MvcMailer NuGet before it hit version 1.0 and now its time to wrap up the NuGet package for an official first release. I got several encouraging feedback on this package and here&#39;s what you get from this first release:&#xA;Use Scaffold Mailer to generate your mailers with views. Compose rich emails using your favorite ASP.NET MVC view engine.Use master pages and pass data using ViewData/ViewBag.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ActionMailer 3 - why do you call instance methods as class/self methods?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/01/28/actionmailer-3-why-do-you-call-instance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/01/28/actionmailer-3-why-do-you-call-instance/</guid>
      <description>I didn&#39;t even notice this little trick! As long as I didn&#39;t have to call deliver_welcome_message (or deliver_*) methods that would magically call welcome_message, I was happy that now the magic is gone. Things are transparent!&#xA;Here&#39;s an example showing the change: Say you have the following mailer:&#xA;class Notifier &amp;lt; ActionMailer::Base&#xA;def welcome_message(new_user)&#xA;#a warm welcome message&#xA;end&#xA;endNow, prior to Rails 3, or ActionMailer 3, you would write the following to actually call this method to get the benefits of ActionMailer magics, such as finding the view based on method name and so on:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social Helpers in ASP.Net MVC3 (Facebook, Twitter, Gravatar etc.)</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/01/14/social-helpers-in-aspnet-mvc3-facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/01/14/social-helpers-in-aspnet-mvc3-facebook/</guid>
      <description> This site shows the examples!&#xA;http://www.asp.net/webmatrix/tutorials/13-adding-social-networking-to-your-web-site&#xA;Now, the social links and buttons are no longer from a third-party source, its straight from Microsoft. I don&#39;t know if this is first-party or second-party :p </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Article at CodeProject: MvcMailer</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/01/13/my-article-at-codeproject-mvcmailer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/01/13/my-article-at-codeproject-mvcmailer/</guid>
      <description>I just released a .Net NuGet package called MvcMailer and to get people super easily started, put an article at CodeProject.com. You are most welcome to the article at&amp;nbsp;http://www.codeproject.com/KB/aspnet/MvcMailerNuGet.aspx&#xA;I welcome your comments and suggestions! Comments Sohan Just released 0.8 and it should work. But please let me know if it doesn&amp;#39;t.&#xA;I also added multi-part emails in version 0.8. You may check that out as well.&#xA;One important change:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C# Named Parameters Can be Very Useful</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/01/07/c-named-parameters-can-be-very-useful/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/01/07/c-named-parameters-can-be-very-useful/</guid>
      <description>Think about the following code example:&#xA;htmlHelper.InputHelper(InputType.CheckBox, name, &#34;true&#34;, true /* useViewData */, false /* isChecked */, true /* setId */, false /* isExplicitValue */, htmlAttributes);&#xA;This line is taken from the source code of ASP.NET MVC, or to be more specific its a line from the InputExtension class. I think the intent of the original developer is clear:&#xA;Add comment next to arguments so that one can easily read the method call without getting lost in a who&#39;s who since there are quite some arguments to pass.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2011: Yet Another New Year</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/01/02/2011-yet-another-new-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/01/02/2011-yet-another-new-year/</guid>
      <description>Dear Readers:&#xA;Happy 2011. 2010 was a great year. Why?&#xA;Defended my&amp;nbsp;MSc thesis&amp;nbsp;after a moderate 16 months of grad school life.Published 3 papers in 3 international conferences.Visited 4 new countries - Netherlands, Sweden, Finland and Norway.Visited a few interesting cities - Vancouver, Victoria, Edmonton.100+ posts on DrinkRails.com.25,000+ visits to my two blogs from all over the world.Developed a fresh new app, Plexina Central, for Wairever Inc.Lived a healthy life.Bought my first (98 Corolla) and second (2000 CR-V) cars (also sold my first car)!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DRY - Total 161 Duplicate ArgumentNullException calls in ASP.Net MVC Source Code</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/12/13/dry-total-161-duplicate/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/12/13/dry-total-161-duplicate/</guid>
      <description>There are 161 occurrences of the following code pattern inside the ASP.Net MVC source code: See details of which class and which line at&amp;nbsp;https://gist.github.com/739523&#xA;method(type argument)&#xA;{&#xA;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;if(argument == null){&#xA;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;throw new ArgumentNullException(&#34;argument&#34;)&#xA;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;}&#xA;...&#xA;}&#xA;So, in total this pattern introduces 312 lines of duplicate code without whitespaces and 644 lines of duplicate code including whitespaces. And the pattern is simple, just check a condition and throw exception if its true.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Jose Valim&#39;s Crafting Rails Applications</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/12/10/book-review-jose-valims-crafting-rails/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/12/10/book-review-jose-valims-crafting-rails/</guid>
      <description>Have you already read this?&#xA;The following excerpt &amp;nbsp;by Jose Valim at the end of the book nicely summarizes it:&#xA;Finally, you understand Rails better. You can explore other areas of the source code, study other Action Controller and Active Models modules, check other generators implementations or read the source of Railties, Engines and Applications with detail! - Jose ValimFor the impatient readers, this is the best in-depth Ruby on Rails related book I have ever read and you should read this (only 172 pages).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ruby - some mysterious language features</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/11/11/ruby-some-mysterious-language-features/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/11/11/ruby-some-mysterious-language-features/</guid>
      <description> Here I will share some of the interesting ruby features that you will notice when looking into mature ruby code by advanced level coders.&#xA;Comments Inventory Management Software Thanks for sharing your post and it was superb .I would like to hear more from you in future too. </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upgrading to Ruby on Rails 3 - beware!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/11/10/upgrading-to-ruby-on-rails-3-beware/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/11/10/upgrading-to-ruby-on-rails-3-beware/</guid>
      <description>Ryan Bates had a series of posts (1, 2&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;3) on upgrading your Rails 2.3.x apps to Rails 3.x and sure they are useful. But if you are really doing that, beware of the following changes that you will need to do. It will take a lot of time for sure if you you have a moderate sized app.&#xA;Upgrading your models:&#xA;Get rid of all validates_xxx_of with appropriate validatesGet rid of all def validate .</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using nil.to_a or whatever.to_a in ruby</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/09/29/using-niltoa-or-whatevertoa-in-ruby/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/09/29/using-niltoa-or-whatevertoa-in-ruby/</guid>
      <description>Ruby is a programming language for developer happiness and productivity for customers. Here is a quick happiness and productivity tip:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 design principles</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/09/18/4-design-principles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/09/18/4-design-principles/</guid>
      <description> Simplicity favors regularity.&#xA;Smaller is faster.&#xA;Good design demands compromise.&#xA;Make the common case fast.&#xA;The four principles of MIPS design that applies to most design jobs we do, even with our personal lives. Agree? </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OO Design Dilemma: Auditing Changes Across Hierarchical Objects</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/09/15/oo-design-dilemma-auditing-changes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/09/15/oo-design-dilemma-auditing-changes/</guid>
      <description>Here is a sample UML class diagram of the situation that posed me the OO design dilemma a few days ago.&#xA;Let me explain with an example,&#xA;The Electronic Items catalog has many Televisions. The Sony Televisions come with different specifications, such as refresh rate of 240 Hz, 120 Hz and 60 Hz. However, the 240 Hz ones also comes in different colors - Black and Grey.Now, a store manager needs to see the recent changes across all catalogs, such as electronic items, musical instruments and so on.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Know Your Enemies Before They Kill You!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/07/19/know-your-enemies-before-they-kill-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/07/19/know-your-enemies-before-they-kill-you/</guid>
      <description>From darekbYou know what, this is a political world. So, enemies will seemingly look like your friends until the moment when.. well, its time for the kill! My dear readers, its time to know the enemies!&#xA;I have met with a few enemies off late. I will go one by one here.&#xA;If you are a software developer like me, you will often see this enemy, camouflaged variables, methods, classes and namespaces.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Greatest Show on Earth and What Else?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/07/07/greatest-show-on-earth-and-what-else/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/07/07/greatest-show-on-earth-and-what-else/</guid>
      <description>FIFA world cup 2010 is almost coming to an end. This is definitely the greatest show on earth and I have been all occupied with the matches...&#xA;However, the show started almost immediately after I was back from Europe. It was a nice tour, starting a day at Amsterdam. Then to Trondheim (Norway), Stockholm and the best part was the night long sea cruise to Helsinki. An experience to remember for the rest of my life.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Summer of 2010! Europe, here we come!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/05/03/summer-of-2010-europe-here-we-come/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/05/03/summer-of-2010-europe-here-we-come/</guid>
      <description>I just completed my Winter 2010 semester at school. It was so far a good one. I pushed my papers and presentations on the courses of this semester at http://smsohan.com/#courses&amp;nbsp;If you are interested to read my paper about Tabletop Application Testing or Communication Challenges with Distributed Agile Teams, you are most welcome at my site.&#xA;However, its time to look ahead to the summer. And I hope this will be a good one!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Authlogic and single access token for API access</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/04/26/using-authlogic-and-single-access-token/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/04/26/using-authlogic-and-single-access-token/</guid>
      <description>Bynarylogic&#39;s authlogic has gained much popularity for its out of the box solution to ruby on rails authentication. Yesterday, I was working on giving API access to my ruby on rails application so that other apps can use my RESTful services. The authenticated API access usually involves the following steps:&#xA;API_KEY or a token to identify/authenticate an API call.Authentication of an API caller using the API_KEY.Authlogic comes with in-built support for this.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>flash.now - did you know?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/03/31/flashnow-did-you-know/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/03/31/flashnow-did-you-know/</guid>
      <description>Well, I didn&#39;t know this until late. If you are like me, you have often wondered when you saw those unwanted flash messages appearing after a request, sometimes after ajax requests when you do a redirect, all on a sudden that flash shows up!&#xA;Well, as you have thought, the Ruby on Rails people have solved this problem way before now. The solution is to wisely use flash.now[] and flash[].</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s up next?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/03/23/whats-up-next/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/03/23/whats-up-next/</guid>
      <description>Hello Readers:&#xA;Wish you all are doing great as the Spring already started :-)&#xA;Recently my grad courses are keeping me busy with assignments and projects as the term comes close to an end. So, I haven&#39;t had much time to spend on blogging other than posting the Ruby on Rails link blog called www.DrinkRails.com. However, for my readers, I thought I would post the recent presentation that I put for the Agile course here:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ruby on Rails Security Review: An Experience Report</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/03/11/ruby-on-rails-security-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/03/11/ruby-on-rails-security-review/</guid>
      <description>Image credits to Wink&amp;nbsp;on Flickr (creative commons)&#xA;I was reviewing a Ruby on Rails source code to see the security implementations they have so far. They are about to launch their product for the first release and wanted to ensure they have the most obvious things checked. So, in a sense it was not supposed to be a hacking job for me, rather to check if the most well known security measures are in place.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ruby on Rails or Rails on Ruby?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/03/09/ruby-on-rails-or-rails-on-ruby/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/03/09/ruby-on-rails-or-rails-on-ruby/</guid>
      <description>All on a sudden, this thing popped up in my mind. What we are calling Ruby on Rails, is this actually &#34;Ruby&#34; on &#34;Rails&#34; or the other way around? Is this upside down? Here&#39;s my mental picture of the RoR framework:&#xA;Image credits to Foo Fighter&amp;nbsp;on Flickr(creative commons)&#xA;Ruby is a self-sustained language. As a language this is completely ignorant of the Rails Framework. So, I think there is no dependency from Ruby to Rails.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rails Source Code Walkthrough #1: the ActiveModel Module</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/02/26/rails-source-code-walkthrough-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/02/26/rails-source-code-walkthrough-1/</guid>
      <description>I was taking a look into the fresh ActiveModel module of Rails 3 as of github revision #100644. Here is what I learned:&#xA;Learned about new feature called autoload. Rails Inside has a small yet useful autoload example here. It is a mechanism to lazy load your modules, so delaying the load unless the module methods are actually called. A call to autoload simply marks it as a potential include, but the actual include takes place only when you first use something on that module.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why would you spend $10 to learn to use Basecamp?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/02/25/why-would-you-spend-10-to-learn-to-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/02/25/why-would-you-spend-10-to-learn-to-use/</guid>
      <description>This is sounding very strange to me indeed! 37Signals is very much known for creating the simplest of interfaces and I really found people finding it very intuitive. But this is strange... now they are asking people to buy a book for $10 to learn how to use Basecamp! Can you believe it? See the sales post (!) here at&amp;nbsp;&#34;Sams Teach Yourself Basecamp in 10 Minutes&#34; is a comprehensive guide to Basecamp Comments Sohan Hi Ashic, thanks for stopping by!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ruby on Rails Interview Questions: Advanced</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/02/23/ruby-on-rails-interview-questions_23/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/02/23/ruby-on-rails-interview-questions_23/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post, I listed a few general interview questions for Ruby on Rails jobs. This one is intended to be more of an advanced level, not for the rookies :-)&#xA;What is Rack?Sketch out a deployment architecture of a Ruby on Rails application utilizing multiple servers.How can you secure a rails application to counter for Session Fixation?Where can I get the core rails framework source code?How can you reuse the models from one rails project into another?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ruby on Rails Interview Questions</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/02/22/ruby-on-rails-interview-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/02/22/ruby-on-rails-interview-questions/</guid>
      <description>Ruby Specific Questions&#xA;The best place for learning ruby is to get started with the programming-ruby. It fairly covers the important bits in a very readable language. Here are a few quick questions on ruby:&#xA;What is rubygems?What is a Symbol?What is the difference between a Symbol and String?What is the purpose of yield?How do you define class variables?How do you define instance variables?How do you define global variables?How can you dynamically define a method body?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uploading files with blog post</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/01/21/uploading-files-with-blog-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/01/21/uploading-files-with-blog-post/</guid>
      <description>At times I wanted to push some files with my blog so that people can download and check something locally. Up until now, it was not a straight-forward way. I either uploaded the file to my own server or google pages or somewhere. Then linked it on the blog.&#xA;However, you can now publish files from Windows Live SkyDrive&amp;nbsp;(total free space of 25 GB)&amp;nbsp;or Google Docs (Total free space 1GB).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experience notes from a RoR code review job</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/01/20/experience-notes-from-ror-code-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/01/20/experience-notes-from-ror-code-review/</guid>
      <description>Recently I had the opportunity to review a ruby on rails code. The project aims to create an online market place for experts, with a similar model to some other freelancing/outsourcing sites. Here is how and what I reviewed:&#xA;I had a read-only access to the code and no download was allowed locally. So, I didn&#39;t get to run the code, tests or any tool to auto-generate some reports on the code.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Home/End key in Mac ( MacBook Pro ) Windows on Bootcamp</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/01/01/homeend-key-in-macbook-pro-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/01/01/homeend-key-in-macbook-pro-windows/</guid>
      <description>If you are anything like me, you love using the home and end key to quickly move to the start/end of a line of text. But, in Apple MacBook Pro, there is no default home/end key! I searched the internet and found Command + Left/Right to the rescue on OS X.&#xA;But, then I installed windows 7 on my Mac and it was nightmare to edit without the home/end keys.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>acts_as_permalinkable: SEO friendly rails URLs using my first RoR plugin</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/12/27/acts-as-permalinkable-seo-friendly/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/12/27/acts-as-permalinkable-seo-friendly/</guid>
      <description>As a byproduct of my work on www.campzero.com, I released my first ruby on rails plugin called acts_as_permalinkable on github athttp://github.com/smsohan/acts_as_permalinkableA comprehensive documentation is given at the github page. If you ever need to use search engine friendly urls or permalink like this blog, you may consider using the acts_as_permalinkable plugin. It takes less than 3 minutes to add the permalink feature to your rails model!Get started by the following and you are free to contribute!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Added Crummy to generate breadcrumbs for CampZero.com</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/12/27/added-crummy-to-generate-breadcrumbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/12/27/added-crummy-to-generate-breadcrumbs/</guid>
      <description>According to google&#39;s SEO guideline, its a good idea to provide breadcrumbs to your web contents. This is good in two ways: a) It helps people to find path to move up the navigation stack and b) it helps the google and other search engines to get a feel about your web content&#39;s hierarchical organization.To add this breadcrumbs support, in my application www.campzero.com, a going to be online service marketplace for Bangladesh, I simply used the Crummy plugin.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sitemap-generator for your Rails App and deployment solution</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/12/24/sitemap-generator-for-your-rails-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/12/24/sitemap-generator-for-your-rails-app/</guid>
      <description>When talking about Search Engine Optimization for your public web pages, you probably try to follow the google guidelines for search engine optimization. Its a good one to get started with. For my recent project, www.campzero.com, I read the document and tried to follow the steps. Today, I worked on generating sitemap for www.campzero.com using the following:Installed the site-map generator plugin following this link at Aktagon&#39;s, github linkFor some reason, probably because of permission issues, my plugin install didn&#39;t generate the sample sitemap.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to strip html tags, truncate and highlight texts in ruby on rails</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/12/22/how-to-strip-html-tags-truncate-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/12/22/how-to-strip-html-tags-truncate-and/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I had the following requirements as I was working on CampZero.com - the going to be service marketplace of Bangladesh.Remove all html tags other than hyperlinks and new lines from a html fragmentTruncate the text to show only first 200 characters of the text and append ellipsis (...) in case the text was truncated.Highlight an array of words in the text to show the search query worlds that matchedThe first one, getting rid of all but hyperlinks and new lines was achieved by the following code:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How is Rails plugins helping me in developing CampZero.com?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/12/18/how-is-rails-plugins-helping-me-in/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/12/18/how-is-rails-plugins-helping-me-in/</guid>
      <description>I am up to a web venture called www.CampZero.com - an online market place for you service providers in Bangladesh. This is somewhat similar in spirit to classified sites like ebay and craigslist, but the target market it consciously chosen to be the service industry. Anyway, I will go to the point why I picked rails for this project and how it is paying off.&#xA;A little background about me.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What I learned from my first semester at University of Calgary as a Grad Student?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/12/15/what-i-learned-from-my-first-semester/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/12/15/what-i-learned-from-my-first-semester/</guid>
      <description>In a single line, the first semester has been awesome.Some of you already know that I came to Calgary, AB, Canada this fall to start a graduate research focusing agile software development. So, to get started I tried to come up with a research idea by hunting several resources including popular publications, blogs and books. This is not yet over...However, I took a course called Applied Machine Learning and had the opportunity to work on a project that might lead to my MS thesis.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lean Thinking: You will probably like to learn the essence of agile</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/11/06/lean-thinking-you-will-probably-like-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/11/06/lean-thinking-you-will-probably-like-to/</guid>
      <description>Image taken from: http://www.leansoftwareinstitute.com/images/img_bigpicture.jpg&#xA;If you read the Poppendieck&#39;s book called, &#34;Lean Software Development : An Agile Toolkit&#34;, you probably liked it because it managed to get the essence out of agile practices. So, what are these core principles? Well, most of you already know the phrase, &#34;Inspect and Adapt&#34;. Now, you also know a bunch of specifications that facilitate this, for an instance, Scrum, XP etc.&#xA;Reading the book, I had a realization that, its good to talk using concrete facts as much as possible.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Now reading: Lean Software Development: An Agile Toolkit</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/10/27/now-reading-lean-software-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/10/27/now-reading-lean-software-development/</guid>
      <description> This book by Mary and Tom Poppendieck is an awesome read. I just read the first three chapters and loving it. More on this book will come later as I read more...I am tuned to attend the next CAMUG session by the Authors! It should be a lightning session and looking forward to Nov 2nd. </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Communicating tools for working on remote projects</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/10/17/communicating-tools-for-working-on/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/10/17/communicating-tools-for-working-on/</guid>
      <description>Ever since I started working in the software industry, as a freelancer or representing a company, I found the most challenging part of a remote software development project is &#34;Communication&#34;. In agile setup, collaboration plays a leading role to be effective and efficient.&#xA;By communication, I mean the following:-Getting the spec as intended by the client.Asking specific questions on time.Status update about progress, blocks and forthcoming events.Getting feedback as intended by the client.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Web application user interface without any Menu</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/10/06/web-application-user-interface-without/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/10/06/web-application-user-interface-without/</guid>
      <description>If you are like me, with little creativity with UI (!), on a new project you always start with a simple layout, banner followed by a row of menu and then a two column body that ends with a footer. Well, here is an example:-----------------------------------------------------------CampZero zero hassle camping----------------------------------------------------------Home | Place a booking----------------------------------------------------------Welcome | | | | | | --------------------------------------------------------- Campzero.com, all rights reserved---------------------------------------------------------Well, there are other ways and you will almost always see good visual elements in most websites.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Showing unread posts/comments: An example of rails ActiveRecord &#39;touch&#39;</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/09/21/showing-unread-postscomments-example-of/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/09/21/showing-unread-postscomments-example-of/</guid>
      <description>I worked on the following story:-&#34;As a partner, when I visit a project&#39;s dashboard I want to see five most recently started or updated discussion threads with number of unread comments, if any. If any of these are new, I want to see them in a highlighted view. Next, if I open the thread, I want to see all new comments in a highlighted view as well. However, once seen, the threads/comments should no longer be highlighted from the rest.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some useful plugins for RoR projects</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/09/17/some-useful-plugins-for-ror-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/09/17/some-useful-plugins-for-ror-projects/</guid>
      <description>Previously I used a few plugins in RoR projects including ScrumPad. On a more recent work, I found the following plugins to be really useful and easy to get started:-&#xA;1. I18n: Rails Internationalization RailsCast at http://railscasts.com/episodes/138-i18n Guides post at http://guides.rubyonrails.org/i18n.html&#xA;2. Seed-fu: Initial data loading for application (e.g. admin user, product categories)Tutorial http://github.com/mbleigh/seed-fu A support is now built in for Rails 2.3.4&#xA;3. Thinking-sphinx: Full text search RailsCast http://railscasts.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The CGI story on agile scaling success on a large project</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/09/09/cgi-story-on-agile-scaling-success-on/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/09/09/cgi-story-on-agile-scaling-success-on/</guid>
      <description>This intro is from the presenters:-&#xA;PAS was a joint venture development initiative by 4 major oil and gas&#xA;companies and CGI. Devon, Encana, Husky and Talisman joined with CGI to&#xA;develop a new Production and Revenue Application. Each company put 3 senior&#xA;business resources on the project. The development component of the PAS&#xA;initiative cost $35M over 5 years with up to 90 people on the team. This</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new home at Calgary and starting days</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/09/06/new-home-at-calgary-and-starting-days/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/09/06/new-home-at-calgary-and-starting-days/</guid>
      <description>We relocated to the northwest section of Calgary, Alberta on the 26th August. I am new to this part of the world and traveling to this opposite time zone (GMT+6 to GMT-6) took around 33 hours. Did you ever take a flight on Qatar? Not? I recommend it. They offer best foods for your south asian delight. My route was Dhaka - Doha - London - Calgary. I enjoyed the trip (don&#39;t tell anyone, I was a bit scared when traveling over the Atlantic :-))</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rambling stories from my days @ Code71 : My Takehome</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/19/rambling-stories-from-my-days-code71-my/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/19/rambling-stories-from-my-days-code71-my/</guid>
      <description>Today is going to be my last day with the Code71 team and this is the last post of the series on my Code71 days.&#xA;The journey started on June 1, 2006 and now at this moment, I just wanted to summarize my takehome from the last three years&#39; of work. I will go short, just touching the bits...Teaming is at the core of Code71&#39;s culture. It went beyond teaming just for software development as we met outside for a movie, celebrated even the smallest of personal achievements and shared the excitement of a cricket or tennis match even at midnight from home over phone!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rambling story from my days @ Code71: My reading list</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/11/rambling-story-from-my-days-code71-my/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/11/rambling-story-from-my-days-code71-my/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post, I got a bit nostalgic! However, ever since I posted the first one, I was looking for another post on the series. Trying to capture what I learned during the past 3 years, I found it would be really time taking for me and my readers. So, I sort of compiled the following list in this post. Hope it helps someone who is just eager to learn about software.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rambling stories from my days @ Code71 : Startup days</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/08/rambling-stories-from-my-days-code71/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/08/rambling-stories-from-my-days-code71/</guid>
      <description>Sighs!&#xA;Back then, on Friday, May 26, 2006, I was a final year undergrad student at CSE, BUET. I was looking for a part-time software dev job opportunity and found a little one page advert for a student job at asha-technologies (lately renamed as Code71). Visited their website and thought it might be worth giving a try!&#xA;As usual, I was interviewed over phone and enjoyed a long 2 hour interview on premise.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rails modeling guide#1: right structure of a ruby on rails model</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/07/16/rails-modeling-guide1-right-structure/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/07/16/rails-modeling-guide1-right-structure/</guid>
      <description>Rails models are no exception compared to the super models! You are in the business if and only if you got a good physical structure and can stick to it for years...&#xA;At Code71, we are keeping our rails models attractive following a few guidelines. I will be posting these guidelines in a series and here goes the first one - about the physical structure of the ruby on rails models.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rails modeling guide#2: naming convention for ruby on rails model methods</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/07/16/rails-modeling-guide2-naming-ruby-on/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/07/16/rails-modeling-guide2-naming-ruby-on/</guid>
      <description>Naming conventions play an important role to the software&#39;s overall architecture. It is not a rocket science, still, it may lead to unhappy consequences if not taken care of at the early stage of a project. This small best practices can make a code base significantly improved.&#xA;Rails does a good job by using the dynamic power of ruby and providing with a handful of dynamic methods with the models.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementing breadcrumb in rails projects – a clean approach</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/07/07/implementing-breadcrumb-in-rails/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/07/07/implementing-breadcrumb-in-rails/</guid>
      <description>In most web applications, breadcrumbs offer a nice way to trace back to previously visited pages. However, generating the breadcrumbs and showing them on dynamic pages sometimes need special care for the following reasons-&#xA;The links of the breadcrumb may contain dynamic links. It is used in all the pages. So, changing the breadcrumb may trigger a series of changes. In ScrumPad, we are using ruby on rails. There are a few plugins to help rails projects in managing breadcrumbs, but none seemed to satisfy our need.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lesson#2: Pace Your Sprint Rightly</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/15/2009-06-15-lesson2-pace-your-sprint-rightly/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/15/2009-06-15-lesson2-pace-your-sprint-rightly/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post, I said about being incremental. Here come the next thing, being “ITERATIVE”. A prefer the term Sprint than Iteration.&#xA;So, once you decided to take small increments, make sure you reach the targets sprinting.&#xA;I suggest you prepare for sprinting with the right techniques and tools. A few recommendations-&#xA;Never miss a daily standup meeting. Spend only 2 minutes (or less) per person answering the three questions – what did you do yesterday, what’s on the plate for today and what is blocking the race?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lesson#2: Pace Your Sprint Rightly</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/15/lesson2-pace-your-sprint-rightly/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/15/lesson2-pace-your-sprint-rightly/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post, I said about being incremental. Here come the next thing, being “ITERATIVE”. A prefer the term Sprint than Iteration.&#xA;So, once you decided to take small increments, make sure you reach the targets sprinting.&#xA;I suggest you prepare for sprinting with the right techniques and tools. A few recommendations-&#xA;Never miss a daily standup meeting. Spend only 2 minutes (or less) per person answering the three questions – what did you do yesterday, what’s on the plate for today and what is blocking the race?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Its easier to get lost! Would you?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/03/its-easier-to-get-lost-would-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/03/its-easier-to-get-lost-would-you/</guid>
      <description>I was talking to a friend of mine, who started a IT start up and working full time with a few others to foster the business. He was telling me-&#xA;“We have 13 projects running at this moment. We are working our heart out. But, we are not finding any time to do Test Driven Development, Continuous Integration and all the good things…”&#xA;Well, I understand how it feels! As the title says, “Its easier to get lost!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lesson#1: Going Incremental is Natural!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/03/lesson1-going-incremental-is-natural/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/03/lesson1-going-incremental-is-natural/</guid>
      <description>As Scrum and Agile processes tell you, do it in small sprints, 2 weeks preferably, and go incremental. Take a small piece at a time and sprint. I took this image from internet and credits to this site.&#xA;It’s easy to work out the Natural way than to defy it! If you are iterative and incremental, you are reaching towards the right hand side of the image! And to make the evolution faster, I suggest you try out Scrumming with ScrumPad.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unit/Functional Test Rails ActionController filters following DRY</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/05/13/unit-test-actioncontroller-filters/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/05/13/unit-test-actioncontroller-filters/</guid>
      <description>At ScrumPad most of our controllers are bounded by filters for authentication/authorization. Some filters apply to all actions in a controller while others apply to only a few or leave out only a few. However, since we are following TDD, we need to test the filter is invoked before each of the desired action. This makes the test code MOIST (not DRY)!&#xA;Example of Moist Code:&#xA;The following example only captures two test methods.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forget Me Not! Object Oriented Design in Custom Exception</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/26/object-oriented-design-in-custom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/26/object-oriented-design-in-custom/</guid>
      <description>When designing custom exceptions, you may forget about old school OO fundamentals. As a reminder, lets take a look into the following custom exception classes.&#xA;StorySaveError&#xA;StoryDescopeNotAllowedError&#xA;StoryCompleteError&#xA;StoryNotFoundError&#xA;StoryDeleteError&#xA;StoryDeleteNotAllowedErrorThese exceptions are really useful in my application. But the bad thing is, they all derive from StandardError class, whereas there should be a base class, may be StoryError, which is more meaningful and useful. So, we can have the following-</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unit Test eager loading in Rails ActiveRecord association</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/21/unit-test-eager-loading-in-rails/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/21/unit-test-eager-loading-in-rails/</guid>
      <description>To avoid the n+1 problem, you need to use eager loading in ActiveRecord object associations. An easy implementation of eager loading can be done using named scope in the following way.&#xA;class User &amp;lt; ActiveRecord::Base&#xA;has_many :friends&#xA;named_scope :eager_load_friends, :include =&amp;gt; :fiends&#xA;end&#xA;User.find(user_id).eager_load_friendsTo unit test the named scope, you can use this following helper method (keep it in test_helper.rb, if you like) that I wrote for ScrumPad&#xA;def test_eager_loaded(model, association)</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementing Template Method in Rails Controllers Using Module and Mixin</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/15/implementing-template-method-in-rails/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/15/implementing-template-method-in-rails/</guid>
      <description>All rails controllers are subclasses of the ApplicationController class. A typical controller class declaration will look like the following-&#xA;class LoginController &amp;lt; ApplicationController&#xA;#the actions go here&#xA;endWith this basic information, I would like to state the problem first.&#xA;The Problem/Job in Hand&#xA;Add an action switch_project to all the controllers (&amp;gt; 20) of the ScrumPad code base. The implementations of the switch_project method will be same for all the controllers only other than the fact that, the switching destination will be different.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing the SyntaxHighlighter Scripts</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/11/testing-syntaxhighlighter-scripts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Apr 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/11/testing-syntaxhighlighter-scripts/</guid>
      <description>For the last few months, I am on the lookout for a really good syntax highlighter that helps me to post blogs on all the programming languages in a pretty html with syntax coloring/highlighting. This one is taken from http://alexgorbatchev.com/wiki/SyntaxHighlighter&#xA;Ruby/Rails class TestHighlighter&#xA;def my_highlighter&#xA;return &#34;SyntaxHighlighter&#34;&#xA;end&#xA;end&#xA;CSharp&#xA;public class TestHighlighter&#xA;{&#xA;public string MyHighlighter&#xA;{&#xA;get {return &#34;SyntaxHighlighter&#34;;}&#xA;}&#xA;}&#xA;What did I add to my blog?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pair Programming: How am I feeling?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/09/pair-programming-how-am-i-feeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/09/pair-programming-how-am-i-feeling/</guid>
      <description>For an explanation of Pair Programming, please visit this wiki entry.&#xA;Good&#xA;I am pair programming on the ScrumPad project now and the feeling in general is good. I have this perception is the work quality is better than doing alone. Also, the amount of time wasted to find small issues are now much reduced. Overall, its good.&#xA;Productivity Increased&#xA;I definitely found the productivity boosted by a factor of 1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>assert_equal_float : assert_equal between two float objects with precision</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/07/assertequalfloat-assertequal-between/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/07/assertequalfloat-assertequal-between/</guid>
      <description>In doing rails unit testing, sometime you need to assert the equality between two float objects in the following fashion&#xA;assert_equal 32.8, object_under_test.method_returning_float&#xA;The internal storage of float objects sometimes will contain 32.8 with additional lower precision decimal points and hence the assert may fail although the significant digits may be same. For example, the value of object_under_test.method_returning_float may be stored as 32.80000001 in memory and the above call may fail.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Looking at ASP.NET MVC</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/05/looking-at-aspnet-mvc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/05/looking-at-aspnet-mvc/</guid>
      <description>Being over-burdened by all the blog posts on MVC from the ASP.Net for the last few months, I am now looking to ASP.Net MVC. Still seeing the tutorials on asp.net/mvc site.&#xA;I have worked on a few rails projects and the ASP.Net MVC implementation is very much like Rails. Anyway, still early for me to comment!&#xA;Comments Sohan @Tanvir,Yes, I read the first chapter. My finding is ASP.Net MVC is still far from being real!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>named_scope : Real life examples from ScrumPad</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/03/30/namedscope-real-life-examples-from/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/03/30/namedscope-real-life-examples-from/</guid>
      <description>I am working on ScrumPad chat refactoring now. In rails 2, the named_scope feature works really great for ActiveRecord models. Lets start with the code first-&#xA;The Source Code:&#xA;class ChatUser &amp;lt; ActiveRecord::Base belongs_to :chat belongs_to :user belongs_to :chat_status, :foreign_key =&amp;gt; &#34;status_id&#34; named_scope :closed, lambda {|chat_id| {:conditions =&amp;gt; [&#34;status_id = #{ChatStatus::CLOSED} AND chat_id = ? &#34;, chat_id]}} do def invite() each { |chat_user| chat_user.update_attribute(:status_id, ChatStatus::INVITED) } end end named_scope :active_chats, lambda {|user_id| {:conditions =&amp;gt; [&#34;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design/Code Review: Now, It&#39;s time to realize!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/03/23/designcode-review-now-it-time-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/03/23/designcode-review-now-it-time-to/</guid>
      <description>Are you doing code reviews?&#xA;Thank God, you are. Not?&#xA;Well, you are not alone. You know, most of your bugs could be killed by reviews. Most of your technical debts could be paid by reviews. Your team could collectively learn more by reviews...&#xA;Now, It&#39;s time to realize!&#xA;Start now! It&#39;s simple. I have found the following approach to be useful-&#xA;Pair up with one developer. Make it explicit to the team.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comet and Server Push (Reverse Ajax) technology</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/03/22/coment-and-server-push-reverse-ajax/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/03/22/coment-and-server-push-reverse-ajax/</guid>
      <description>I am re-implementing an ajax based chat system. Presently an ajax request is polled continuously to look for any updates/messages from the user’s browser. However, the plan is to use the server to push the messages to the clients to off-load the server from a huge number of useless ajax calls.&#xA;I learned about Comet and found it interesting. You may read about comet here at WIKI.&#xA;Juggernaut is a rails plug-in that uses Flash to implement the server push technology.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Juggernaut on Linux</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/03/22/juggernaut-on-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/03/22/juggernaut-on-linux/</guid>
      <description>I just installed Juggernaut on my linux box. The installation is simpler than windows. At least it gave me less pain.&#xA;Just run the following commands-&#xA;gem install json gem install activemachine gem install juggernaut juggernaut –g juggernaut.yml juggernaut –c juggernaut.yml I got a little pain regarding the g++ compiler that is required to build the activemachine. I did not have it installed in my Amazon EC2 instance and after some searches, I could install it using the following-</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The RANK() Function for Numbering on Groups/Partitions in SQL Server</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/03/06/rank-function-for-numbering-on/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/03/06/rank-function-for-numbering-on/</guid>
      <description>Previously, I used the ROW_NUMBER() function to get the monotonically increasing row number of a result set from a SQL query. But, this time the requirement was a bit different as follows.&#xA;I have many combinations of Year, Make, Model and Trim of vehicles in my database. I also have potential profit on sale of each of the combinations. I need to produce, the top 5 trims for a Year, Make, Model combination that yields maximum profits.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Working on a Data Warehouse project</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/02/22/working-on-data-warehouse-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/02/22/working-on-data-warehouse-project/</guid>
      <description>I have been busy for the last month as we, at Code71, rolled out the first release of the Business Intelligence project for Vuneu Media. I will give you a brief on my project here so that you can follow my coming posts.&#xA;The used vehicle dealers buy their vehicles from different Auctions across the country. When making a buy decision, they try to find answer to these questions-</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A good example of C# Regular Expression: Implementing InitCap or Titleize/TitleCase using C# and Regular Expression</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/01/21/good-example-of-c-regular-expression/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/01/21/good-example-of-c-regular-expression/</guid>
      <description>Ever since I first learned about the regular expressions, I have always been fascinated by its magical capability. When I first learned about DFA/NFA, I figured out how it is possible to evaluate a regular expression and eventually, during my Undergrad at BUET, I implemented a regular expression evaluator for the Compiler Lab.&#xA;Now, given this history, here is a simple code that I wrote today. Let me know if you liked it-</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asp.Net Membership: How to change a user&#39;s password from an admin account without knowing the current password?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/12/23/aspnet-membership-how-to-change-user/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/12/23/aspnet-membership-how-to-change-user/</guid>
      <description>Like mine, you may also need to change a user&#39;s password from an admin account. By default, when you are using ASP.Net authentication and storing the password in the hashed format, you will not be able to see the existing password in its decrypted form. Also, to change a password using the Membership API, you will need to know the existing password. However, here is a simple solution to the problem -</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solution to JavaScript File Include Problem From ASP.Net MasterPage</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/12/23/solution-to-javascript-file-include/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/12/23/solution-to-javascript-file-include/</guid>
      <description>You can include javascript files using a simple script tag. However, you will soon discover that, when you are using this master page from content pages that are at different levels in folder hierarchy then the script files will be missing at some cases. This is due to the fact that, script file paths are referenced relative to the content page and NOT to the master page. As a result, despite having the correct include wrt the master page, your content pages may still miss the scripts!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Part 1: How am I IMPACTing following Scrum?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/11/26/part-1-how-am-i-impacting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/11/26/part-1-how-am-i-impacting/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post in this blog, I introduced the nice little acronym IMPACT for agile. To recap, here is what IMPACT stands for -&#xA;&#34;Iterative and Incremental development of a software by means of Merciless refactoring, Peer reviews, Automated acceptance testing, Continuous integration and of course, Test driven development&#34;&#xA;To give you a little background around my story, let me tell you about a project that I am working since June 2006.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Delving into client side capabilities of ASP.Net Ajax</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/11/18/delving-into-client-side-capabilities/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/11/18/delving-into-client-side-capabilities/</guid>
      <description>I believe the client side scripting capabilities of ASP.Net Ajax is not utilized by many ASP.Net developers. This is most probably due to the fact that, not many people are aware of it at the first place. Also, since most of the javascripts are rendered secretly (read, not blatantly, which is good), most developers don&#39;t even feel the existence of the underlying javascript at all.&#xA;Two very simple examples of the client side library are given here as examples -</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IMPACTing for agile software development</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/11/18/impact-of-agile-software-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/11/18/impact-of-agile-software-development/</guid>
      <description>Well, next time on a dev job interview when someone asks you the question, &#34;Can you give us a brief idea on agile software development engineering practices?&#34;, you are probably gonna laugh on your mind and just answer, &#34;IMPACT!&#34;. Yes, this is it, compact and right on target!&#xA;Today, I came up with this acronym about agile engineering practices and I think its a nice one :-)&#xA;IMPACT can be elaborated as follows-</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RowTest Extension for NUnit</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/11/10/rowtest-extension-for-nunit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/11/10/rowtest-extension-for-nunit/</guid>
      <description>Well, I was just about to implement it myself! However, its good to see that the NUnit addin named RowTest actually allows us to do the data driven unit test through declarative programming and adding parameters to the dumb test methods!&#xA;http://www.andreas-schlapsi.com/projects/rowtest-extension-for-nunit/&#xA;Check out this website for an example and get started with RowTest.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iterative and Incremental implementation of Code Reviews</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/11/03/iterative-and-incremental/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/11/03/iterative-and-incremental/</guid>
      <description>Extreme Programming (XP) advocates for a pair-programming, taking the code review to its extreme. I have also found that pair programming generates a lot of speed and also helps producing better quality product in the first time. But, at the same time it&#39;s difficult to impress the management or prove return on investment associated with pair programming to the business people. So, what is the best possible solution? I believe, we can implement frequent peer code reviews to mimic the pair programming to some extent and get the benefit out of it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CruiseControl.Net (CCNet) configuration example for NCover</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/09/06/cruisecontrolnet-ccnet-configuration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/09/06/cruisecontrolnet-ccnet-configuration/</guid>
      <description>CruiseControl.Net is a great continuous integration tool for .Net projects. It not only continuously builds your software but provides some really helpful reports to monitor your project&#39;s progress.&#xA;In agile world, we all speak of self-testing code or test driven development (TDD). If we really want to ensure our code has enough test coverage, we need to use some tool to ease our lives and NCover is a good one for this purpose.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BDD - My First BDD Code using RSpec in Ruby</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/09/01/bdd-my-first-bdd-code-using-rspec-in/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/09/01/bdd-my-first-bdd-code-using-rspec-in/</guid>
      <description>I am really really happy to see people putting so much efforts for building high quality, nearly all avoidable error free software. I am a big believer of Test Driven Development and doing TDD for about two years now. I have always had the feeling that TDD is a kind of a misnomer because to some people the term &#39;Test&#39; refers to finding bugs. For this very reason, when people gets started with TDD, they consider it as a waste of time to write so much extra code that doesn&#39;t necessarily find bugs!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Set and Compile using C# Language Version 2.0 in Visual Studio 2008</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/09/01/set-and-compile-using-c-language/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/09/01/set-and-compile-using-c-language/</guid>
      <description>I know, while most of you are very happy with the new features in Visual Studio 2008, its sad that not all your deployment environments are upgraded to .Net framework 3.5. I had a similar situation as well on one of my projects.&#xA;Its great that you can just navigate to a VS 2008 project file properties and from the Application Tab select the Target .Net Framework version to use one of .</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Target items still in the 2008 learning Queue</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/20/my-target-items-still-in-2008-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/20/my-target-items-still-in-2008-learning/</guid>
      <description>1. Windows Workflow foundation.&#xA;2. Study about ERP and take a good look into a popular open-source ERP application.&#xA;3. Study on SOA.&#xA;4. Study on Smart Client applications.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unit Testing using Mocks - FillWithMocks, Fill all or only selected properties with Mocks using only a single method call</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/13/unit-testing-using-mocks-fillwithmocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/13/unit-testing-using-mocks-fillwithmocks/</guid>
      <description>I have been doing TDD for about two years now and using mock testing for interaction based unit testing in my projects. What I have learned over this time is, a unit testable design leads to introduction of interfaces and dependency injection for testing a code in isolation. And when I want to perform tests on my interactions, I need to create mock objects and inject these mock instances to my object under test.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>XDocument.ToStringWithXmlDeclaration() - Get the string representation of XDcoument with its Xml Declaration</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/12/xdocumenttostringwithxmldeclaration-get/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/12/xdocumenttostringwithxmldeclaration-get/</guid>
      <description>The System.Xml.Linq.XDocument.ToString() produces a serialized string version of the XDocument object. But unfortunately, while doing so, it leaves the xml declaration in the serialized version which may be required in your application.&#xA;Again, there is another method called Save that produces the serialized version including xml declaration. So, I think we can write a simple extension method for producing the xml declaration as shown in the following -&#xA;14 class Program</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simple Wildcard replacement on the Rendered Html of Asp.Net Page</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/11/simple-wildcard-replacement-on-rendered/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/11/simple-wildcard-replacement-on-rendered/</guid>
      <description>This is a simple solution for implementing wildcard replacements in your asp.net pages. You may use this, if you want to replace some tokens / merge codes in the asp.net generated html by your personalized values. System.Web.UI.Control has a virtual method called &#39;Render&#39; of the following signature - protected internal virtual void Render( HtmlTextWriter writer )&#xA;Since, all your ASP.Net pages and server controls are subclasses of this Control class, you can override this method and manipulate the html that&#39;s rendered from this control.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Log4Net SmtpAppender and sending emails with log messages</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/07/log4net-smtpappender-and-sending-emails/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/07/log4net-smtpappender-and-sending-emails/</guid>
      <description>Since my client asked me if it was possible to generate emails for log entries on an error/fatal level I took a look into the Log4Net SmtpAppender. In your project you may need to implement a similar function and in that case you may use a log4net configuration like the following one- 93 &amp;lt;appender name=&#34;SmtpAppender&#34; type=&#34;log4net.Appender.SmtpAppender&#34;&amp;gt;&#xA;94 &amp;lt;to value=&#34;&#34; /&amp;gt;&#xA;95 &amp;lt;from value=&#34;&#34; /&amp;gt;&#xA;96 &amp;lt;Username value=&#34;&#34;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/Username&amp;gt;&#xA;97 &amp;lt;password value=&#34;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing with NULL in where clause using Linq to SQL</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/05/comparing-with-null-in-where-clause-in/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/05/comparing-with-null-in-where-clause-in/</guid>
      <description>In SQL Server, a SQL statement like &#39;NULL=NULL&#39; evaluates to false. however &#39;NULL IS NULL&#39; evaluates to true. So, for NULL values in your database columns, you need to use the &#39;IS&#39; operator instead of the regular &#39;=&#39; operator.&#xA;The problem is, in Linq to SQL, there is no such &#39;IS&#39; operator since &#39;IS&#39; is already used as a C# language keyword. So, when you are invoking an equality check in your Linq to SQL where clause to a nullable column you need to be alert on this behavior.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JQuery - I will consider using it in my future web project</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/04/jquery-i-will-consider-using-it-in-my/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/04/jquery-i-will-consider-using-it-in-my/</guid>
      <description>I find the problems with cross-browser issues with Javascript to be bothering at times. Also, I am most annoyed with Javascript because, with Javascript, I need to think about another programming language along with my server side programming. I have a feeling that Javascript codes make the web application harder to test using various automated test frameworks and adds complexities as there are different browsers who interpret the Javascript code in different ways.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ninject - Dependency Injection Framework for .Net Objects</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/03/ninject-dependency-injection-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/08/03/ninject-dependency-injection-framework/</guid>
      <description>I loved Ninject because&#xA;- I don&#39;t love to write/edit XML documents myself.&#xA;- I think Ninject can save a lot of coding and debugging time.&#xA;- This is a cool framework :-) with a fun-to-read documentation.&#xA;- It uses simple conventions and Attributes for resolving most dependencies behind the scene.&#xA;- You can take full advantage to lambda expressions for writing compact codes.&#xA;Today, I took a look into this Ninject framework.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>[ThreadStatic] - A cool Attribute to Thread Safe static members</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/06/10/threadstatic-cool-attribute-to-thread/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/06/10/threadstatic-cool-attribute-to-thread/</guid>
      <description>Usually static variables holds the same value for all the threads running at the same AppDommain. However, in a multithreaded scenario, you may need to add thread safe behavior to your static members so that the value of a static member is same inside only a single thread and across multiple threads the value can be different. In this way you may attain a thread specific or thread scoped storage to use in your application.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simple Article on REST using WCF</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/06/08/simple-article-on-rest-using-wcf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/06/08/simple-article-on-rest-using-wcf/</guid>
      <description>For a few days, I have been trying a lot to understand why people would be using RESTful instead of the standard SOAP based Web Services. I thought, I could better understand by building one little RESTfully architected application myself.&#xA;After a few google searches, I found that WCF has some attribute based programming support for implementing a RESTful architecture. MSDN has a good document on the whole WebGet and WebInvoke attributes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enable IntelliSense support for Spring.Net objects xml definition</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/28/enable-intellisense-support-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/28/enable-intellisense-support-for/</guid>
      <description>Spring.Net has integration support with VS 2005 and VS 2008 (also supports older versions). To achieve this, just perform a simple copy-paste and define an XML namespace on the objects node. This will enable you to get IntelliSense and validation support while editing the objects node of the xml configuration file.&#xA;Two steps:&#xA;Step 1: Copy the &amp;lt;Spring.Net Installed location&amp;gt;\doc\schema\spring-objects-1.1.xsd to &amp;lt;Visual Studio installed location&amp;gt;/Xml/Schemas&#xA;Step 2: Make sure your objects node looks like this &amp;lt;objects xmlns=&#34;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>INVEST - Characteristics of Effective User Stories</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/28/invest-characteristics-of-effective/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/28/invest-characteristics-of-effective/</guid>
      <description>In Agile Software Development, for example SCRUM and XP, User Story is a tool to capture the requirements from the clients. The term User Story takes a very free form. Sometimes, we feel that there needs to be a boundary so that a user story is an effective one and not misused. I have a feeling that INVEST defines the border line on this regard.&#xA;The INVEST principle is a very good guideline for defining user stories in an agile environment.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Article at CodeProject on LINQ to SQL  DataContext CommandTimeout</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/23/my-article-at-codeproject-on-linq-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/23/my-article-at-codeproject-on-linq-to/</guid>
      <description>CodeProject has published my article at &#39;Change The Default CommandTimeout of LINQ DataContext&#39; I have discussed the topic covered in this article on a previous blog post at this link.&#xA;Please read the article and provide me with your feedback.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Read My Article at CodeProject on LINQ to Log4Net Logging</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/14/read-my-article-at-codeproject-on-linq/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/14/read-my-article-at-codeproject-on-linq/</guid>
      <description>Today CodeProject has published an article of mine where I have shown a way to use Log4Net logging to capture your LINQ to SQL class generated log messages. I suggest you all to take a look and comment at http://www.codeproject.com/KB/linq/LINQ2Log4Net.aspx.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Try the CopySourceAsHTML VS Addin to blog .Net Codes</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/14/try-copysourceashtml-vs-addin-to-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/14/try-copysourceashtml-vs-addin-to-blog/</guid>
      <description>I have just found a great add-in for blogging my codes preserving the styles exactly the same as that I see in VS 2008. I am surely going to use it in future posts.&#xA;Follow the steps here - http://blogs.microsoft.co.il/blogs/bursteg/archive/2007/11/21/copy-source-as-html-copysourceashtml-for-visual-studio-2008-rtm.aspx</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Page_ClientValidate - Use this Method from Javascript for ASP.Net Client Side Validation</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/11/pageclientvalidate-use-this-method-from/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/11/pageclientvalidate-use-this-method-from/</guid>
      <description>In a typical ASP.Net web form, we have a few controls and also validators associated with the controls. The most common validators are used for Required Field validation, Type validation, Regular Expression validation and so on.&#xA;When we want to logically group the validators in a web form, we apply the same value for ValidationGroup property on the controls of a group and in this way, we create a logical division among our controls and the validation.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Article on Unit Testing Events in C# 3.0</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/04/article-on-unit-testing-events-in-c-30/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/04/article-on-unit-testing-events-in-c-30/</guid>
      <description>Please read this article to find out an interesting way to write unit tests on your events.&#xA;http://www.dotnettoad.com/index.php?/archives/12-unit-testing-events.html&#xA;Unit testing has always seemed rather easy and annoying to most of the people who are new to test driven development for the reason because there is not much room for coding other than the Assert methods. Yet, I have found that people actually starts finding it cool once they have written some test codes and stuck at a point where it offers the &#39;Challenge&#39; to really write a clean and concise test code.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How To Set Default Application Wide CommandTimeout in LINQ to SQL DataContext Subclasses</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/29/how-to-set-default-application-wide/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/29/how-to-set-default-application-wide/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes you have written long running stored procedures and you need to invoke the stored procedures through your LINQ to SQL class. By default the SqlCommand has a timeout value of 30 seconds and in some instances you may need a longer value to complete your long running database operations. In a situation like this, if you are using the default time out value, you may encounter the following exception scenario,</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>string.GetValueOrDefault() - A Simple Extension Method</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/16/stringgetvalueordefault-simple/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/16/stringgetvalueordefault-simple/</guid>
      <description>I have found that, I have written codes like the following one in my projects before now at some places.&#xA;string myString = someString == null ? string.Empty : someString;&#xA;However, with the advent of extension methods in C# 3.0 (.Net 3.5), I have a better way of achieving this goal in my projects. So, I just wrote an extension method as the following one-&#xA;public static class StringExtensions { public static string GetValueOrDefault(this string instance) { return instance == null ?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Best of Today&#39;s RSS from My Daily Feeds</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/14/best-of-today-rss-from-my-daily-feeds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/14/best-of-today-rss-from-my-daily-feeds/</guid>
      <description>1. If using LINQ gives you a great feeling, then I suggest you to read this post (to make it feel even better) where you learn about a less used keyword called &#39;let&#39; to make your LINQ queries more readable and human friendly.&#xA;http://www.codethinked.com/post/2008/04/The-Linq-quot3bletquot3b-keyword.aspx</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IsNullOrEmpty() - A Handy Extension Method for IEnumerable&lt;T&gt;</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/12/isnullorempty-handy-extension-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/12/isnullorempty-handy-extension-method/</guid>
      <description>Many a time when you are just about to write a foreach loop on your IEnumerable&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; object you need to check whether the object is null or empty in the following manner&#xA;if(myEnumerable != null || myEnumerable.Count() &amp;gt; 0) { foreach(&amp;lt;type&amp;gt; item in myEnumerable) { ... } } However, with the advent of Extension methods, you can write one custom extension method like the following -&#xA;public static class IEnumerableExtensions { public static bool IsNullOrEmpty&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(this IEnumerable&amp;lt;T&amp;gt; instance) where T : class { return instance == null || instance.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Today&#39;s best RSS feeds</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/12/my-today-best-rss-feeds/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/12/my-today-best-rss-feeds/</guid>
      <description>1. Well, we have a CI in place and we are also very excited to see a new notification message coming to our email inbox on a commit from our team members. CruiseControl.Net really made is fun and so easy to be really continuously integrating our projects.&#xA;However, I didn&#39;t know of this cool feature until I read this article. I suggest you all CruiseControl.Net cruisers to take a look -</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Best RSS Feed I have read today</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/09/best-rss-feed-i-have-read-today/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/09/best-rss-feed-i-have-read-today/</guid>
      <description>Many a times, if feels great to know about the online users and some more details about them when they are on your website. This article gives you the code example to achieve this in your ASP.Net application.&#xA;http://www.aspdotnetfaq.com/Faq/How-to-get-detailed-info-about-all-online-visitors-that-are-currently-browsing-your-ASP-NET-website.aspx</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Posts of the day that I liked most</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/08/posts-of-day-that-i-liked-most/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/08/posts-of-day-that-i-liked-most/</guid>
      <description>1. The Monostate Pattern - Another way to look into Singleton and some improvement over singleton issues.&#xA;Read it Here&#xA;2. Another good article on LINQ regarding the grouping queries. Read it Here</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creating Instances of internal classes using Spring.Net</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/07/creating-instances-of-internal-classes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/07/creating-instances-of-internal-classes/</guid>
      <description>Creating an instance of an internal class using Spring.Net is a little tricky. I know that, you can achieve this by adding an InternalsVisibleTo attribute to your assembly. However, the following solution also works as desired.&#xA;Say, you have an namespace named SampleClasses that contains the a public interface named &#39;IPublicInterface&#39; and also an internal class named &#39;InternalClass&#39; that implements the IPublicInterface interface and looks like the following - 1: namespace SampleClasses</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logging the LINQ to SQL Generated SQL Queries/Commands</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/07/logging-linq-to-sql-generated-sql/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/07/logging-linq-to-sql-generated-sql/</guid>
      <description>I was looking for logging solutions for the generated SQL in one of my projects where I am using LINQ to SQL. I found that sometimes the the Exceptions and StackTrace information does not say much about what&#39;s really causing the problem with LINQ to SQL queries/commands.&#xA;To see the actual SQL that&#39;s generated from LINQ you may write a code like the following-&#xA;SampleDataContext context = new SampleDataContext(); //You may wish to use any subclass of System.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My First Post Using Windows Live Writer</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/06/my-first-post-using-windows-live-writer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/04/06/my-first-post-using-windows-live-writer/</guid>
      <description>I came to know about this cool writer very recently and was waiting to take a look at this editor. Now that I am writing a blog entry from this editor, I feel like its really making my life easy.&#xA;Well, for a head start, I just hit the print screen button followed by a ctrl-V and this is what you see! It&#39;s lot more fun to edit in this editor!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My MCTS Certification</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/25/my-mcts-certification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/25/my-mcts-certification/</guid>
      <description> Today I have appeared at the MCTS Exam # 70-528 (Web Based Client Development) and successfully passed the exam. I also appeared at another exam # 70-536 (Microsoft .Net Framework) and successfully passed in that exam too.&#xA;Although, I haven&#39;t got the MCP website access information yet, I can now possibly be called a &#39;Microsoft Certified Technology Specialist&#39;! </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A solution to the problem with creating mocks for interfaces with Generic Methods with NMock</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/20/solution-to-problem-with-creating-mocks/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/20/solution-to-problem-with-creating-mocks/</guid>
      <description>I was so happy with NMock to see how it can dynamically generate mocks of interfaces and also gives me a fluent interface to write expectations and everything it does to help me in unit testing!&#xA;However, I could not generate dynamic mocks for interfaces with Generic methods and it kept showing me the &#39;TypeLoadException&#39; on and on. My interface looks like the following -&#xA;interface IObjectFactory&#xA;{&#xA;T GetObject(string id);</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Verify Correct DateTime data in method call using NMock</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/18/verify-correct-datetime-data-in-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/18/verify-correct-datetime-data-in-method/</guid>
      <description>Recently I was writing unit test for a method of the following signature&#xA;interface ICache&#xA;{&#xA;void Insert(string key, object value, DateTime absoluteExpiration, TimeSpan slidingExpiration);&#xA;}&#xA;and I wanted to verify the following call -&#xA;Insert(&#34;key&#34;, &#34;value&#34;, DateTime.Now.AddMinutes(30), TimeSpan.Zero);&#xA;However, you readily see the problem in verifying with the above call for the presence of DateTime.Now.AddMinutes(30) in the argument. So, a test method like the following won&#39;t work for obvious reason.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mock Internal Interface with NMock2 - Use InternalsVisibleToAttribute</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/16/mock-internal-interface-with-nmock2-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/16/mock-internal-interface-with-nmock2-use/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I badly needed to create mocks for my internal interfaces. I am using NMock2 as a Mocking framework and found it really difficult to produce Mocks for internal interfaces. After some &#39;google time&#39; and investigation I found that you need the following two lines in your AssemblyInfo.cs to achieve this purpose-&#xA;[assembly: InternalsVisibleTo(&#34;Mocks&#34;)]&#xA;[assembly: InternalsVisibleTo(&#34;MockObjects&#34;)]&#xA;Where are the two assemblies? I found that these two assemblies are dynamically created by NMock2 for mocking your interfaces.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unity - A Dependency Injection framework from Microsoft Patterns and Practices</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/15/unity-dependency-injection-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/15/unity-dependency-injection-framework/</guid>
      <description>I have been using Spring.Net for implementing Dependency Injection in my .Net projects. Spring is already one of the most known providers of DI in the Java world and a port to .Net actually eased the lives of people like me who are willing to develop unit-testable software.&#xA;However, with all the happiness enjoyed through Spring.Net, I guess its time to take a look into Unity. I have only started using this and I found it interesting in the sense that its more of .</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Internal Class in .Net C#</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/11/testing-internal-class-in-net-c/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/11/testing-internal-class-in-net-c/</guid>
      <description>I have been to a situation where only a small number of classes had been declared as public classes in an assembly. And most of the classes are declared as internal, because I wanted to expose only the public classes to the consumers of my assembly.&#xA;However, doing so creates another challenge in testing the internal classes. As we most commonly want our test codes to reside on a separate assembly so that we can leave that assembly out when we are releasing the end product.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What does a Scrum Master really do?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/08/what-does-scrum-master-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/08/what-does-scrum-master-do/</guid>
      <description>Hmm! I am now a CSM (Certified Scrum Master) after two days of training with CST Pette Deemer.&#xA;You want to congratulate me! Lets congratulate me first-&#xA;You: Congratulations! It&#39;s really a great news! How does it feel to be a CSM?&#xA;Me: Greaaaaaaaat! You know, its so cool that my profile gets a CSM on it!&#xA;You: Oh Sohan! I am so sure that you will contribute more at the company?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preserve Ownership, mode and other attributes while copying in Linux</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/02/13/preserve-ownership-mode-and-other/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/02/13/preserve-ownership-mode-and-other/</guid>
      <description>I dare not say, I am savvy at Linux :-)&#xA;Recently, I ran into a problem where I found that upon executing a copy command, my source and destination files had different permissions and attributes (i-nodes), but I badly needed the permissions to be preserved in the destination files/folders. The following command will preserve the attributes -&#xA;cp -p source destination here, the switch p (-p) does the trick, it preserves the permissions, modes and other attributes to resemble the source.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C# keyword &#39;yield return&#39; - I find it interesting</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/02/05/c-keyword-yield-return-i-find-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/02/05/c-keyword-yield-return-i-find-it/</guid>
      <description>I have been using yield return in some of my codes and would like to share its interesting aspects. The following code example shows one dummy use of &#39;yield return&#39;-&#xA;public class YieldExample&#xA;{&#xA;public void Run()&#xA;{&#xA;IEnumerator numbers = getNumbers().GetEnumerator();&#xA;while (numbers.MoveNext())&#xA;{ Console.Write(&#34;x{0} &#34;, numbers.Current);&#xA;}&#xA;}&#xA;private IEnumerable getNumbers()&#xA;{&#xA;for (int i = 0; i &lt;&gt;&#xA;Now, a code like new YieldExample().Run() would produce a output similar to this - &#34;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C# 3.0 Anonymous types - actual type depends on the order of the property assignnments</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/02/04/c-30-anonymous-types-actual-type/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/02/04/c-30-anonymous-types-actual-type/</guid>
      <description>I learned that the anonymous types in C# 3.0 has got a good feature that, if you have two anonymous declarations with the same signature, then you create only one anonymous type and have two instances of the type.&#xA;So, a code fragment like the following is perfectly valid and passes all compiler warnings/errors-&#xA;var anon = new { FirstName = &#34;first&#34;, Age = 21 };&#xA;var anon2 = new { FirstName = &#34;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Easiest and the Hardest Methods to write unit test for</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/12/02/easiest-and-hardest-methods-to-write/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/12/02/easiest-and-hardest-methods-to-write/</guid>
      <description>I was wondering to find out the easiest methods to write unit tests for. I came up with a few results as the following ones...&#xA;a. A method that takes no parameter, perform calculations on only local data and always returns a constant value is the easiest to test. But the question is, is this at all important to have such methods?&#xA;b. A method that takes some parameters, and limits its operations only on the supplied parameters and local variables and returns some value or throws exception is also very easy to write a test for.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unit Testing void Methods - Part 1</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/12/02/unit-testing-void-methods-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/12/02/unit-testing-void-methods-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Dissection of void Methods without parameters&#xA;Methods with void return types incur complexities in writing unit tests. So, we need to characterize the void methods to make sure we have guards against the odds for testability.&#xA;A typical void method without any parameter looks like the following&#xA;public void DoSomething()&#xA;{&#xA;//1.modifies some member variables&#xA;this.someMemberVariable = 10;&#xA;//2.Calls methods of the same class or other classes&#xA;someClass.SomeOtherMethod(someArg);&#xA;//3.Sometimes throws exception</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unit Testing void Methods - Part 2</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/12/02/unit-testing-void-methods-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/12/02/unit-testing-void-methods-part-2/</guid>
      <description>Dissection of void Methods with parameters&#xA;Methods with void return types incur complexities in writing unit tests. So, we need to characterize the void methods to make sure we have guards against the odds for testability.&#xA;For example, the following is a void method with parameters&#xA;public void DoSomething(SomeType obj, SomeOtherType objOther)&#xA;{&#xA;//1.modifies some member variables&#xA;this.someMemberVariable = 10;&#xA;//2.Calls methods of the same class or other classes</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Object Graphs and Dependency Injection</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/12/01/graph-of-objects-and-dependency/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/12/01/graph-of-objects-and-dependency/</guid>
      <description>An application is supposed to have a graph of objects as a result of the following-&#xA;1. Objects are designed to be interacting with each other following two rules of thumb &#34;Highest Cohesion&#34; and &#34;Lowest coupling&#34;. So, a class instead of taking all the responsibilities only takes care of some high cohesive ones and depends on other partner classes for the rest of the services. This dependency creates a graph like structure with objects as the nodes and dependencies as the edges.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prerequisites for IID</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/11/28/prerequisites-for-iid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/11/28/prerequisites-for-iid/</guid>
      <description>Up to now, I have figured out that teams trying to behave agile sometimes fall into the cave of pretending to be agile (e.g. stand up meetings and less than just enough planning and short iterations so on!). Often, when this pretending takes places for days, it creates a illusion on the minds of the people that they might be doing the &#34;right thing&#34;. And all on a sudden, someone discovers things are breaking and there is no way out of this disaster!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two Aspects of Agile Software Development Process</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/11/28/two-aspects-of-agile-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/11/28/two-aspects-of-agile-software/</guid>
      <description>I have been in practice with the famous agile software development process called &#34;Scrum&#34; for more than a year. I have had the opportunity to see a SCRUM team developing from scratch in a completely start-up environment.&#xA;I will point to the two aspects as,&#xA;1. Management aspects.&#xA;2. Technical aspects.&#xA;1. Management aspects&#xA;I encapsulate the things like working on a story by story basis, standing up for daily status update meeting, producing deliveries in short iterations and without much of prior planning into this group.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
