<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Other on Sohan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://smsohan.com/categories/other/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Other on Sohan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://smsohan.com/categories/other/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Context</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/09/15/context/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/09/15/context/</guid>
      <description>Image credits to NCinDC&#xA;Context is everything. Due to a context mismatch projects such as exporting democracy, agile transformations, building startups, losing weight, mindfulness or anything you can think of fail to repeat.&#xA;Context is formed by why / what / who / when / where / how, each of these being a critcial part. Most often it&amp;rsquo;s common to focus on the how alone - forgetting the rest of the context while adopting a recipe for success in business.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Play at Work</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/07/04/play-at-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/07/04/play-at-work/</guid>
      <description>Image source: [Kalvis](https://www.flickr.com/photos/hgz/) &amp;ldquo;I am a mango&amp;rdquo;.&#xA;First, mangoes are in-season, and I still remember the juicy sweetness of the mango I had just the night before. So, when the coach asked each of us to be a fruit, I didn&amp;rsquo;t think twice. One of my coworkers was a kiwi, another one apple, and so on. The idea was to group us by color, then by size. This got us, twenty people in the class, moving and engaged.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Annual letter</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2016/12/18/annual-letter-to-myself-and-to-the-www/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2016/12/18/annual-letter-to-myself-and-to-the-www/</guid>
      <description>2016 Highs and lows Baby #2, it&amp;rsquo;s a girl Shera, our little daughter, was born this year. She has been happy, healthy, and an absolute source of joy. Almost hard to believe that we somehow sustained the pregnancy period of my wife, while also running after our active toddler son, Shopoth. Such a pleasure to see the two already reaching for one another, cuddling, giggling, and occasionally fighting.&#xA;Canadian Citizenship, eh!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RailsConf 2015</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/05/08/railsconf-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/05/08/railsconf-2015/</guid>
      <description>I have finally been able to attend a RailsConf, the 2015 edition was my first ever. And I got to say hi to people like @dhh, @wycats, and many more. Thanks Cisco for sponsoring this trip.&#xA;The attendance on the conference was totally amazing, heaven knows how many, but it looked like a couple thousands of rails developers attended the @dhh keynote. And @dhh delivered a good one. Unlike the last year&amp;rsquo;s talk, this year it didn&amp;rsquo;t cause a huge noise because it was mostly about announcing new features of rails to be released with Rails 5.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lessons Learned: Entrepreneurship and Innovation Course</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/12/09/lessons-learned-entrepreneurship-and-innovation-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/12/09/lessons-learned-entrepreneurship-and-innovation-course/</guid>
      <description>This fall semester, I signed for the Entrepreneurship and Innovation course (ENTI 781) at the Haskyne Business School of University of Calgary. Wanted to capture my thoughts on this course for my readers here.&#xA;First, the course was unconventional since there are very little academic material to teach entrepreneurship and innovation. The teacher, Olga Petricevic, did a decent job of collecting materials comprising of academic papers, case studies, newspaper articles and YouTube videos as well as bringing in a local entrepreneur for a lecture one day.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>100 Miles, a 100 Miles...</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/10/31/100-miles/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/10/31/100-miles/</guid>
      <description>So, on the 18th of October, 2014, I&amp;rsquo;ve completed my goal of running a 100 miles in 50 days and wanted to share some data for my readers. Enjoy!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Year 2014</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/01/30/the-year-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/01/30/the-year-2014/</guid>
      <description>2013 was an amazing year in many ways for my personal life. To recap, the top story of 2013 was of course the birth of our son, Shopoth. And then, we bought our first house, paid off our car-loan and ended the year with a much needed vacation, that too to Bangladesh where we spent some quality time with the families.&#xA;2013 was my year of learning Haskell. I can&amp;rsquo;t claim to be a seasoned Haskell programmer yet.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rejecting Because It Didn&#39;t Work Last Time</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/01/24/rejecting-because-it-didnt-work-last-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/01/24/rejecting-because-it-didnt-work-last-time/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip; is as right as &amp;ldquo;the weather will be bad today because it wasn&amp;rsquo;t any good yesterday&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Programming Language Should I Learn in 2013?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/12/12/what-programming-language-should-i-learn-in-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/12/12/what-programming-language-should-i-learn-in-2013/</guid>
      <description>I like the idea of learning one new programming language every year. This is also mentioned at The Pragmatic Programmer Book. I&amp;rsquo;m now looking for a new language to learn.&#xA;In 2011, I learned F#, my first functional programming language experience. It&amp;rsquo;s a really nice language, especially if you&amp;rsquo;re familiar with the .Net class library and the windows development echo system in general. This was really fun, learned the basic concepts and building blocks of functional languages.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joined Sourcefire</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/10/22/joined-sourcefire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2012/10/22/joined-sourcefire/</guid>
      <description>Hello Dear Readers:&#xA;I just wanted to inform you that I&amp;rsquo;ve joined Sourcefire this morning as a Principal Software Engineer. My primary responsibility will be helping my team with Ruby on Rails and Web technology related expertise. I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to this new role.&#xA;ThoughtWorks was a wonderful experience. In the last couple of years with ThoughtWorks, I have worked on 4 different projects, for 4 different clients and business domains from 4 different cities in North America.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Avoid Duplication in Config Files</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/07/11/avoid-duplication-in-config-files/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/07/11/avoid-duplication-in-config-files/</guid>
      <description>Any kind of configuration file, be it an ugly xml file or a prettier yml or properties file, its been a source of frustration to me. Here&#39;s a list of few such pain points:&#xA;There are two config keys that point to the same value. e.g. db_username=master, data_source_user=masterThere are two config keys for urls that point to the same domain, but different paths. e.g. market.com/cameras and market.com/undiesConfig entries with placeholders.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Not To Provide Feedback When Doing Code Review</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/06/25/how-not-to-provide-feedback-when-doing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/06/25/how-not-to-provide-feedback-when-doing/</guid>
      <description>Code review, as any other review process, can often be an attack on someone&#39;s ego and incite anger and frustration. Being both on sending and receiving end of such code reviews for years, I have learned a few how-not-to-do-it, or as one might say, anti-patterns of providing code review feedback. Let me know if you agree/disagree with me on the following:&#xA;You are always reviewing Adam&#39;s code while Adam is never reviewing yours.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My 2011 Q1 developer roadmap</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/03/14/my-2011-q1-developer-roadmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/03/14/my-2011-q1-developer-roadmap/</guid>
      <description>For me, 2011 Q1 has so far been a good exposure to new techniques, tools, articles and books, thanks to ThoughtWorks book allowance! However, if you are interested, here&#39;s what&#39;s keeping me busy:&#xA;User Experience: I find a good user experience is THE thing that you want in anything you design, and if you are writing a software, its even more important. After I read a few books, I have a feeling that its not just a common sense approach, it takes some education and a deep care to produce something usable.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2011: Yet Another New Year</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/01/02/2011-yet-another-new-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2011/01/02/2011-yet-another-new-year/</guid>
      <description>Dear Readers:&#xA;Happy 2011. 2010 was a great year. Why?&#xA;Defended my&amp;nbsp;MSc thesis&amp;nbsp;after a moderate 16 months of grad school life.Published 3 papers in 3 international conferences.Visited 4 new countries - Netherlands, Sweden, Finland and Norway.Visited a few interesting cities - Vancouver, Victoria, Edmonton.100+ posts on DrinkRails.com.25,000+ visits to my two blogs from all over the world.Developed a fresh new app, Plexina Central, for Wairever Inc.Lived a healthy life.Bought my first (98 Corolla) and second (2000 CR-V) cars (also sold my first car)!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Know Your Enemies Before They Kill You!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/07/19/know-your-enemies-before-they-kill-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/07/19/know-your-enemies-before-they-kill-you/</guid>
      <description>From darekbYou know what, this is a political world. So, enemies will seemingly look like your friends until the moment when.. well, its time for the kill! My dear readers, its time to know the enemies!&#xA;I have met with a few enemies off late. I will go one by one here.&#xA;If you are a software developer like me, you will often see this enemy, camouflaged variables, methods, classes and namespaces.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Greatest Show on Earth and What Else?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/07/07/greatest-show-on-earth-and-what-else/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/07/07/greatest-show-on-earth-and-what-else/</guid>
      <description>FIFA world cup 2010 is almost coming to an end. This is definitely the greatest show on earth and I have been all occupied with the matches...&#xA;However, the show started almost immediately after I was back from Europe. It was a nice tour, starting a day at Amsterdam. Then to Trondheim (Norway), Stockholm and the best part was the night long sea cruise to Helsinki. An experience to remember for the rest of my life.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Summer of 2010! Europe, here we come!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/05/03/summer-of-2010-europe-here-we-come/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/05/03/summer-of-2010-europe-here-we-come/</guid>
      <description>I just completed my Winter 2010 semester at school. It was so far a good one. I pushed my papers and presentations on the courses of this semester at http://smsohan.com/#courses&amp;nbsp;If you are interested to read my paper about Tabletop Application Testing or Communication Challenges with Distributed Agile Teams, you are most welcome at my site.&#xA;However, its time to look ahead to the summer. And I hope this will be a good one!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why would you spend $10 to learn to use Basecamp?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/02/25/why-would-you-spend-10-to-learn-to-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/02/25/why-would-you-spend-10-to-learn-to-use/</guid>
      <description>This is sounding very strange to me indeed! 37Signals is very much known for creating the simplest of interfaces and I really found people finding it very intuitive. But this is strange... now they are asking people to buy a book for $10 to learn how to use Basecamp! Can you believe it? See the sales post (!) here at&amp;nbsp;&#34;Sams Teach Yourself Basecamp in 10 Minutes&#34; is a comprehensive guide to Basecamp Comments Sohan Hi Ashic, thanks for stopping by!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uploading files with blog post</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/01/21/uploading-files-with-blog-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/01/21/uploading-files-with-blog-post/</guid>
      <description>At times I wanted to push some files with my blog so that people can download and check something locally. Up until now, it was not a straight-forward way. I either uploaded the file to my own server or google pages or somewhere. Then linked it on the blog.&#xA;However, you can now publish files from Windows Live SkyDrive&amp;nbsp;(total free space of 25 GB)&amp;nbsp;or Google Docs (Total free space 1GB).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Home/End key in Mac ( MacBook Pro ) Windows on Bootcamp</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/01/01/homeend-key-in-macbook-pro-windows/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2010/01/01/homeend-key-in-macbook-pro-windows/</guid>
      <description>If you are anything like me, you love using the home and end key to quickly move to the start/end of a line of text. But, in Apple MacBook Pro, there is no default home/end key! I searched the internet and found Command + Left/Right to the rescue on OS X.&#xA;But, then I installed windows 7 on my Mac and it was nightmare to edit without the home/end keys.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Web application user interface without any Menu</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/10/06/web-application-user-interface-without/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/10/06/web-application-user-interface-without/</guid>
      <description>If you are like me, with little creativity with UI (!), on a new project you always start with a simple layout, banner followed by a row of menu and then a two column body that ends with a footer. Well, here is an example:-----------------------------------------------------------CampZero zero hassle camping----------------------------------------------------------Home | Place a booking----------------------------------------------------------Welcome | | | | | | --------------------------------------------------------- Campzero.com, all rights reserved---------------------------------------------------------Well, there are other ways and you will almost always see good visual elements in most websites.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rambling stories from my days @ Code71 : My Takehome</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/19/rambling-stories-from-my-days-code71-my/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/19/rambling-stories-from-my-days-code71-my/</guid>
      <description>Today is going to be my last day with the Code71 team and this is the last post of the series on my Code71 days.&#xA;The journey started on June 1, 2006 and now at this moment, I just wanted to summarize my takehome from the last three years&#39; of work. I will go short, just touching the bits...Teaming is at the core of Code71&#39;s culture. It went beyond teaming just for software development as we met outside for a movie, celebrated even the smallest of personal achievements and shared the excitement of a cricket or tennis match even at midnight from home over phone!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rambling story from my days @ Code71: My reading list</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/11/rambling-story-from-my-days-code71-my/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/11/rambling-story-from-my-days-code71-my/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post, I got a bit nostalgic! However, ever since I posted the first one, I was looking for another post on the series. Trying to capture what I learned during the past 3 years, I found it would be really time taking for me and my readers. So, I sort of compiled the following list in this post. Hope it helps someone who is just eager to learn about software.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rambling stories from my days @ Code71 : Startup days</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/08/rambling-stories-from-my-days-code71/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/08/rambling-stories-from-my-days-code71/</guid>
      <description>Sighs!&#xA;Back then, on Friday, May 26, 2006, I was a final year undergrad student at CSE, BUET. I was looking for a part-time software dev job opportunity and found a little one page advert for a student job at asha-technologies (lately renamed as Code71). Visited their website and thought it might be worth giving a try!&#xA;As usual, I was interviewed over phone and enjoyed a long 2 hour interview on premise.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing the SyntaxHighlighter Scripts</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/11/testing-syntaxhighlighter-scripts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Apr 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/11/testing-syntaxhighlighter-scripts/</guid>
      <description>For the last few months, I am on the lookout for a really good syntax highlighter that helps me to post blogs on all the programming languages in a pretty html with syntax coloring/highlighting. This one is taken from http://alexgorbatchev.com/wiki/SyntaxHighlighter&#xA;Ruby/Rails class TestHighlighter&#xA;def my_highlighter&#xA;return &#34;SyntaxHighlighter&#34;&#xA;end&#xA;end&#xA;CSharp&#xA;public class TestHighlighter&#xA;{&#xA;public string MyHighlighter&#xA;{&#xA;get {return &#34;SyntaxHighlighter&#34;;}&#xA;}&#xA;}&#xA;What did I add to my blog?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Try the CopySourceAsHTML VS Addin to blog .Net Codes</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/14/try-copysourceashtml-vs-addin-to-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/05/14/try-copysourceashtml-vs-addin-to-blog/</guid>
      <description>I have just found a great add-in for blogging my codes preserving the styles exactly the same as that I see in VS 2008. I am surely going to use it in future posts.&#xA;Follow the steps here - http://blogs.microsoft.co.il/blogs/bursteg/archive/2007/11/21/copy-source-as-html-copysourceashtml-for-visual-studio-2008-rtm.aspx</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My MCTS Certification</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/25/my-mcts-certification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/25/my-mcts-certification/</guid>
      <description> Today I have appeared at the MCTS Exam # 70-528 (Web Based Client Development) and successfully passed the exam. I also appeared at another exam # 70-536 (Microsoft .Net Framework) and successfully passed in that exam too.&#xA;Although, I haven&#39;t got the MCP website access information yet, I can now possibly be called a &#39;Microsoft Certified Technology Specialist&#39;! </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What does a Scrum Master really do?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/08/what-does-scrum-master-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/08/what-does-scrum-master-do/</guid>
      <description>Hmm! I am now a CSM (Certified Scrum Master) after two days of training with CST Pette Deemer.&#xA;You want to congratulate me! Lets congratulate me first-&#xA;You: Congratulations! It&#39;s really a great news! How does it feel to be a CSM?&#xA;Me: Greaaaaaaaat! You know, its so cool that my profile gets a CSM on it!&#xA;You: Oh Sohan! I am so sure that you will contribute more at the company?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preserve Ownership, mode and other attributes while copying in Linux</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/02/13/preserve-ownership-mode-and-other/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/02/13/preserve-ownership-mode-and-other/</guid>
      <description>I dare not say, I am savvy at Linux :-)&#xA;Recently, I ran into a problem where I found that upon executing a copy command, my source and destination files had different permissions and attributes (i-nodes), but I badly needed the permissions to be preserved in the destination files/folders. The following command will preserve the attributes -&#xA;cp -p source destination here, the switch p (-p) does the trick, it preserves the permissions, modes and other attributes to resemble the source.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
