<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Career on Sohan's Blog</title><link>http://smsohan.com/categories/career/</link><description>Recent content in Career on Sohan's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://smsohan.com/categories/career/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Onboarding as a New Engineering Manager</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/08/09/onboarding-as-a-new-engineering-manager/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/08/09/onboarding-as-a-new-engineering-manager/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;I promise to take care of you&amp;rdquo; - believe it or not, I spent hours to come up with this message to make a first impression as a newly hired manager at Microsoft. Everyone in my team had more context than me. I was a complete newbie, yet their manager. While I had been a manager for several years, I had never started a new job as a manager. I felt super vulnerable.</description></item><item><title>Can I Have a Career as a Frontend Engineer?</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/02/19/frontend-engineering/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/02/19/frontend-engineering/</guid><description>In my current role at Microsoft, I&amp;rsquo;m working on a UI SDK product. I hear this concern from some of my team members. More specifically, here&amp;rsquo;s a paraphrased version of what I hear:
&amp;ldquo;I talked to my friends in software and they told me it&amp;rsquo;s better to work on the backend or full-stack to have a fast-tracked career.&amp;rdquo;
First, I do agree that there are generally more full-stack or backend engineering jobs than purely frontend jobs.</description></item><item><title>"you're unfrogettable"</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/24/you-are-unfrogettable/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/12/24/you-are-unfrogettable/</guid><description>This card is a parting gift from my beloved team. (Catherine, I know you made it)
This post is dedicated to my team at Cisco. I put a lot of my passion and care into building and being part of a great team during my time at Cisco, eight amazing years between 2012 to 2020. It was the privilege of a lifetime to be able to learn from and mentor an amazing group of people while building a product together.</description></item><item><title>Where to Learn: 10 Ways I Do</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/18/where-to-learn/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/18/where-to-learn/</guid><description>When talking to people, I&amp;rsquo;m always interested to know how they learn. This image above shows a view of how I personally learn. Here&amp;rsquo;s some context about the items on the diagram:
Online-courses: I love O&amp;rsquo;Reilly learning. Their video courses are split into 5 minute lectures. For example, I took their Kotlin course to learn the language. Books: Books are great for curated content, but it takes dedicated time. Most of the time, I have one book that I read.</description></item><item><title>Learn to Get and Give Feedback</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/12/learn-to-get-and-give-feedback/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/11/12/learn-to-get-and-give-feedback/</guid><description>Photo credits to GotCredit
Here’s a personal story about getting a feedback. For context, English is my second language. I grew up speaking Bangla as my primary language. I learned reading and writing English in school - grammar first. I had only started speaking English much later in my life, in my mid-twenties. So, I often struggle with the informal form of the language. With this context, here’s an excerpt of a one:one chat conversation at work (from memory):</description></item><item><title>Working With Me</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/02/08/working-with-me/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/02/08/working-with-me/</guid><description>Since I commonly work with a diverse group of people, this post is a way for me to broadcast some quick tricks that may help our working relationship. When we work together, let&amp;rsquo;s do this:
Trust is only earned when it&amp;rsquo;s mutual. Let&amp;rsquo;s work with this shared belief.
Context is everything. Most importantly, show me why we need to work on something. If the answer isn&amp;rsquo;t clear in your mind, we can work together to build a crisp context.</description></item><item><title>Internal Trainings</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/06/27/internal-trainings/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2019/06/27/internal-trainings/</guid><description>Design Thinking course, Cisco Calgary Office, AB, 2019 One benefit of working at Cisco is access to the many learning and development resources. Our learning and development org arranges hundreds of courses throughout the year. Moreover, we have a reimbursement program for external courses, conferences, books, and subscriptions to online learning programs and publications.
In the past 6 years, I have immensely benefitted from these resources. Here&amp;rsquo;s a list of the learning resources I&amp;rsquo;ve used.</description></item><item><title>On Reference Checks: Don'ts</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/09/07/on-reference-checks-donts/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/09/07/on-reference-checks-donts/</guid><description>Most people eventually come across a time when they&amp;rsquo;d need to provide names of colleagues as references while applying for a new job. The referees are often involved in the last stage of the hiring process, when the employer is generally satisfied that the candidate is a potential hire. At this stage, the employer expects to find a few things:
Verification of facts. The employer wants to confirm the validity of the information such as the role, responsibilities, and achievements provided by the candidate about their past experience.</description></item><item><title>So you want to be a software developer. Where to start?</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/02/28/so-you-want-to-be-a-software-developer-where-to-start/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/02/28/so-you-want-to-be-a-software-developer-where-to-start/</guid><description>You didn&amp;rsquo;t go to college to study computer science and you have no background on computer programming. You&amp;rsquo;re not quite happy with your current job area, and looking forward to something more rewarding and exciting. You&amp;rsquo;ve heard software development is generally a good area and often times people without any prior software background can actually get a job. But where do you start?
First, you&amp;rsquo;re thinking in the right direction, and I can assure you that if you like making things and have a nack for problem-solving, you can learn the skills to become a programmer.</description></item><item><title>Why do you want this new job?</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/02/27/why-do-you-want-this-new-job/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2017/02/27/why-do-you-want-this-new-job/</guid><description>No matter which side of the table you&amp;rsquo;ve sat during interviews, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably heard this question: &amp;lsquo;Why do you want this new job?&amp;rsquo;
In the recent past, I&amp;rsquo;ve interviewed a few candidates and heard the following answers so far:
I&amp;rsquo;m not learning much on the current job after it&amp;rsquo;s been 2-4 years. I&amp;rsquo;m looking for something that offers better work-life balance. I&amp;rsquo;m not really looking for a job. The recruiters got in touch and I thought I&amp;rsquo;d discuss.</description></item></channel></rss>