<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Others on Sohan's Blog</title><link>http://smsohan.com/categories/others/</link><description>Recent content in Others on Sohan's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://smsohan.com/categories/others/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What Drives Me?</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/01/16/what-drives-me/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2021/01/16/what-drives-me/</guid><description>First, working with good people for a good purpose. Then, moving fast and delivering incrementally. Then, a good business case. And finally, a reasonably modern tech-stack.
Other things, such as pay, promotion and prestige are important, but it doesn’t drive me like the above.
This content is suitable for a Twitter post, but putting it here for long term retention. I want to look back after a few years to see how timeless this drivers are for me.</description></item><item><title>When I Applied KonMari to My Calendar</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/07/17/when-i-applied-kon-mari-to-my-calendar/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2020/07/17/when-i-applied-kon-mari-to-my-calendar/</guid><description>“I&amp;rsquo;d like to tidy up the entire planet. I would go anywhere if there were something that needs tidying.” - Marie Kondo
Well, she came to my work calendar in spirit. Let’s start with some backstory.
When I was developer, my typical day looked like this: one standup meeting and then pretty much the rest of the day in coding. Sometimes I paired up or jumped on a whiteboard session with my coworkers to hash things out.</description></item><item><title>Rails: Please include a JS test runner</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/03/23/rails-please-include-a-js-test-runner/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/03/23/rails-please-include-a-js-test-runner/</guid><description>For an opinionated framework like Ruby on Rails, I expect it to come pre-bundled with a CoffeeScript based test framework and test runner. Here&amp;rsquo;s why:
Teams don&amp;rsquo;t need to waste time deciding which one to use among the mess of Jasmine, Mocha, Expect, Sinon, Chai, Bower, Grunt, Teaspoon, Npm&amp;hellip; you name it.
It&amp;rsquo;d work better than what&amp;rsquo;s out there since the Rails team will focus on clean integration with Rails and will have a much larger user base to collect contribution from.</description></item><item><title>2015</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/01/02/2015/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2015/01/02/2015/</guid><description>This is a much shorter new year post. 2014 was the year of focusing on health, soft-skills, Haskell, social contribution and PhD in addition to typical everyday stuff. Hoping 2015 will be the year of:
reconnecting with friends and relatives
perfection
While Facebook and Twitter make it easy to browse through my friends&amp;rsquo; photos and status updates, I feel quite reluctant to interact on these media. Also, this passive mode of keeping in touch sucks, since my friends are largely unaware of the fact that I still care.</description></item><item><title>What's wrong with the default alert rendered by the browser?</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/11/20/whats-wrong-with-the-default-alert-rendered-by-the-browser/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/11/20/whats-wrong-with-the-default-alert-rendered-by-the-browser/</guid><description>Browsers have carefully crafted the alert and confirm dialogs for everyone under really simple APIs as follows:
alert(&amp;#39;Failed to send the email. Check your network connection.&amp;#39;); confirm(&amp;#39;Are you sure you want to delete this email?&amp;#39;); While writing cross-browser JavaScript is not as painful today, custom implementation of these natively supported dialogs seem to be a complete waste of money and time to me. With all the different browsers that we have to support today, including the mobile browsers, it seems a lot of wasted effort in trying to render a custom alert and confirm dialog under any circumstance.</description></item><item><title>50 Miles!</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/10/01/50-miles/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/10/01/50-miles/</guid><description>In my previous post about the 100 Miles Challenge, I shared my goal to complete a 100 mile run in 50 days. And I&amp;rsquo;m happy to reach the 50 Miles milestone on day 24, happened this Saturday! 46 Miles to go now, but the target sure looks reachable from here.
I changed a few things on my end. After running for the first couple of weeks, I found my legs weren&amp;rsquo;t feeling great.</description></item><item><title>100 Miles in 50 Days Challenge</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/09/12/100-miles-in-50-days-challenge/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2014/09/12/100-miles-in-50-days-challenge/</guid><description>Weightloss is a tough chase. I&amp;rsquo;ve attempted many times and failed.
Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo of day 2, when I ran my first 5K in years.
Last year I decided to change the focus. Instead of aiming for weightloss, I started aiming for a better lifestyle. To some extent, that worked. But I can&amp;rsquo;t say it really made a big difference of any sort.
I always thought I was a team sport person and hated doing anything only by myself, so much so that, I need a partner even for swimming.</description></item><item><title>Career choices: Should I take this job?</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/09/19/career-choices-should-i-take-this-job/</link><pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/09/19/career-choices-should-i-take-this-job/</guid><description>I get intimidated by this question, &amp;ldquo;Should I take this job?&amp;rdquo;
Growing up, my dad had a huge influence on my upbringing. He had a government job and it was the only job he ever had (retired in 2012). However, my generation Y seems somewhat lucky to be able to pick and choose a job, once every couple years or so. And every time I feel like it&amp;rsquo;s time to start looking around for that next job, I get intimidated by this question.</description></item><item><title>Will You Put That Cell Phone Away?</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/08/27/will-you-put-that-cell-phone-away/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/08/27/will-you-put-that-cell-phone-away/</guid><description>I know it&amp;rsquo;s your phone and you can do anything you want. But may be it&amp;rsquo;s worth holding back at times. There&amp;rsquo;s more to life than our screens.
I&amp;rsquo;m leaving it off the hand, off the table and off the bed, in silent mode, all day long. I&amp;rsquo;m asking for permission to use it if I have to while I&amp;rsquo;m with others. Instead of spending the time with the screens, it&amp;rsquo;s been very rewarding to play with my little son, with all the attention on him.</description></item><item><title>MicroOptimization Trap</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/30/microoptimization-trap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/30/microoptimization-trap/</guid><description>Yesterday, couple of my friends and I were discussing about a CoffeeScript topic. In short, given the following code in CoffeeScript:
class Cat type: -&amp;gt; &amp;#39;cat&amp;#39; meow: -&amp;gt; &amp;#39;meow meow mee..ow&amp;#39; The compiler produces this in JavaScript:
var Cat; Cat = (function() { function Cat() {} Cat.prototype.type = function() { return &amp;#39;cat&amp;#39;; }; Cat.prototype.meow = function() { return &amp;#39;meow meow mee..ow&amp;#39;; }; return Cat; })(); As you see here, the prototype method definitions use the prefix Cat.</description></item><item><title>Call me Sohan and Ask-Me-Not about S M</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/05/call-me-sohan-and-ask-me-not-about-sm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/04/05/call-me-sohan-and-ask-me-not-about-sm/</guid><description>I have heard this question n times, where n tends to the number of days since June 2006, as I started working with the people from North America:
Should I call you S M?
Well, I&amp;rsquo;m from Bangladesh and even today, we don&amp;rsquo;t really have a first and last name, instead what we have is, a full name and a nick name. My full name is, S M Sohan, and my nick name is Sohan.</description></item><item><title>MvcMailer and Open Source Happiness</title><link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/03/18/mvcmailer-and-open-source-happiness/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2013/03/18/mvcmailer-and-open-source-happiness/</guid><description>MvcMailer makes me happy as a developer.
I find an immense amount of happiness everytime I check the Nuget page of MvcMailer. It&amp;rsquo;s so refreshing to see the download count going up (42,427 total downloads as I write), receiving feedback, praises and even the complains.
The idea of MvcMailer came from trying to bring some of the amazing Ruby on Rails ActionMailer features to ASP.NET MVC developers. It was well accepted since the very beginning and I hope is still helping people.</description></item></channel></rss>