<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>scrum on Sohan&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://smsohan.com/categories/scrum/</link>
    <description>Recent content in scrum on Sohan&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://smsohan.com/categories/scrum/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The CGI story on agile scaling success on a large project</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/09/09/cgi-story-on-agile-scaling-success-on/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/09/09/cgi-story-on-agile-scaling-success-on/</guid>
      <description>This intro is from the presenters:-&#xA;PAS was a joint venture development initiative by 4 major oil and gas&#xA;companies and CGI. Devon, Encana, Husky and Talisman joined with CGI to&#xA;develop a new Production and Revenue Application. Each company put 3 senior&#xA;business resources on the project. The development component of the PAS&#xA;initiative cost $35M over 5 years with up to 90 people on the team. This</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rambling stories from my days @ Code71 : Startup days</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/08/rambling-stories-from-my-days-code71/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/08/08/rambling-stories-from-my-days-code71/</guid>
      <description>Sighs!&#xA;Back then, on Friday, May 26, 2006, I was a final year undergrad student at CSE, BUET. I was looking for a part-time software dev job opportunity and found a little one page advert for a student job at asha-technologies (lately renamed as Code71). Visited their website and thought it might be worth giving a try!&#xA;As usual, I was interviewed over phone and enjoyed a long 2 hour interview on premise.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lesson#2: Pace Your Sprint Rightly</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/15/2009-06-15-lesson2-pace-your-sprint-rightly/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/15/2009-06-15-lesson2-pace-your-sprint-rightly/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post, I said about being incremental. Here come the next thing, being “ITERATIVE”. A prefer the term Sprint than Iteration.&#xA;So, once you decided to take small increments, make sure you reach the targets sprinting.&#xA;I suggest you prepare for sprinting with the right techniques and tools. A few recommendations-&#xA;Never miss a daily standup meeting. Spend only 2 minutes (or less) per person answering the three questions – what did you do yesterday, what’s on the plate for today and what is blocking the race?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lesson#2: Pace Your Sprint Rightly</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/15/lesson2-pace-your-sprint-rightly/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/15/lesson2-pace-your-sprint-rightly/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post, I said about being incremental. Here come the next thing, being “ITERATIVE”. A prefer the term Sprint than Iteration.&#xA;So, once you decided to take small increments, make sure you reach the targets sprinting.&#xA;I suggest you prepare for sprinting with the right techniques and tools. A few recommendations-&#xA;Never miss a daily standup meeting. Spend only 2 minutes (or less) per person answering the three questions – what did you do yesterday, what’s on the plate for today and what is blocking the race?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Its easier to get lost! Would you?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/03/its-easier-to-get-lost-would-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/03/its-easier-to-get-lost-would-you/</guid>
      <description>I was talking to a friend of mine, who started a IT start up and working full time with a few others to foster the business. He was telling me-&#xA;“We have 13 projects running at this moment. We are working our heart out. But, we are not finding any time to do Test Driven Development, Continuous Integration and all the good things…”&#xA;Well, I understand how it feels! As the title says, “Its easier to get lost!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lesson#1: Going Incremental is Natural!</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/03/lesson1-going-incremental-is-natural/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/06/03/lesson1-going-incremental-is-natural/</guid>
      <description>As Scrum and Agile processes tell you, do it in small sprints, 2 weeks preferably, and go incremental. Take a small piece at a time and sprint. I took this image from internet and credits to this site.&#xA;It’s easy to work out the Natural way than to defy it! If you are iterative and incremental, you are reaching towards the right hand side of the image! And to make the evolution faster, I suggest you try out Scrumming with ScrumPad.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pair Programming: How am I feeling?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/09/pair-programming-how-am-i-feeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2009/04/09/pair-programming-how-am-i-feeling/</guid>
      <description>For an explanation of Pair Programming, please visit this wiki entry.&#xA;Good&#xA;I am pair programming on the ScrumPad project now and the feeling in general is good. I have this perception is the work quality is better than doing alone. Also, the amount of time wasted to find small issues are now much reduced. Overall, its good.&#xA;Productivity Increased&#xA;I definitely found the productivity boosted by a factor of 1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What does a Scrum Master really do?</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/08/what-does-scrum-master-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2008/03/08/what-does-scrum-master-do/</guid>
      <description>Hmm! I am now a CSM (Certified Scrum Master) after two days of training with CST Pette Deemer.&#xA;You want to congratulate me! Lets congratulate me first-&#xA;You: Congratulations! It&#39;s really a great news! How does it feel to be a CSM?&#xA;Me: Greaaaaaaaat! You know, its so cool that my profile gets a CSM on it!&#xA;You: Oh Sohan! I am so sure that you will contribute more at the company?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prerequisites for IID</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/11/28/prerequisites-for-iid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/11/28/prerequisites-for-iid/</guid>
      <description>Up to now, I have figured out that teams trying to behave agile sometimes fall into the cave of pretending to be agile (e.g. stand up meetings and less than just enough planning and short iterations so on!). Often, when this pretending takes places for days, it creates a illusion on the minds of the people that they might be doing the &#34;right thing&#34;. And all on a sudden, someone discovers things are breaking and there is no way out of this disaster!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two Aspects of Agile Software Development Process</title>
      <link>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/11/28/two-aspects-of-agile-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://smsohan.com/blog/2007/11/28/two-aspects-of-agile-software/</guid>
      <description>I have been in practice with the famous agile software development process called &#34;Scrum&#34; for more than a year. I have had the opportunity to see a SCRUM team developing from scratch in a completely start-up environment.&#xA;I will point to the two aspects as,&#xA;1. Management aspects.&#xA;2. Technical aspects.&#xA;1. Management aspects&#xA;I encapsulate the things like working on a story by story basis, standing up for daily status update meeting, producing deliveries in short iterations and without much of prior planning into this group.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
